<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The XXIV cases concerning things indifferent in religious worship considered, or, The resolver better resolved by his own principles, and non-conformists more confirmed also, the grand case touching ministers conformity, with the double supplement thereunto annexed, briefly discussed.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11692425</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11692425</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 10:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The XXIV cases concerning things indifferent in religious worship considered, or, The resolver better resolved by his own principles, and non-conformists more confirmed also, the grand case touching ministers conformity, with the double supplement thereunto annexed, briefly discussed.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671. Great question concerning things indifferent in religious worship briefly stated.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second part of: The great question concerning things indifferent in religious worship briefly stated / E. Bagshaw.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Bagshaw. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The XXIV Caſes CONCERNING THINGS INDIFFERENT IN Religious Worſhip Conſidered. OR THE RESOLVER Better Reſolved by his own Principles; AND NON-CONFORMISTS More Confirmed. ALSO THE GRAND CASE Touching Miniſters Conformity, with the double Supplement thereunto Annexed, Briefly Diſcuſſed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 15.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Happy is he that condemneth not himſelf, in that thing which he Alloweth.</p>
               <p>And, Happy is he that alloweth not himſelf, in that thing which he Condemneth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:48221:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48221:2"/>
            <head>Queſtion. <hi>Whether Things Inexpedient, or purely Indifferent (ſuch as our</hi> (Engliſh) <hi>Ceremonies are) may be Impoſed by men lawfully in the Worſhip of God? Or, if Impoſed, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be ſubmitted, aſſented, and conſented unto?</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Grand Queſtion hath three Heads of Diſpute; Of the Lawfulneſs 1. Of the Impoſition of them in Worſhip. 2. Of Submiſſion to them as to Practiſe. 3. Of the Declaration of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to all and every thing contained in, and preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer,</hi> or by the Late <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline.</hi> The Probleme hath reſpect only or chiefly to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to the Deciſion of it, I ſhall do theſe three things. 1. Explain the Terms. 2. Shew how far the Diſſenting Parties agree. 3. Undertake to prove the Negative in all the Particulars, upon the Caſuiſts own Principles and Conceſſions.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>I. <hi>Explication of the Terms.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ceremonies.</hi>] I begin with this, partly to diſtinguiſh between Ceremonies, and Circumſtances of Worſhip, which commonly in this Diſpute are confounded; and partly to draw down the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <hi>a Theſi,</hi> as diſcourſed in general under the Notion of Things <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> and purely Indifferent (as it is warily done by the Rev. <hi>Caſuist,</hi> and others, which affords them ſome Creep holes, and Liberty of Evaſion) <hi>ad Hypotheſin</hi> in ſpecial to our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, of which the Controverſie is. And the Definition of a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony will clearly difference it from a Circumſtance of Worſhip. Every Ceremony may be conſidered as a circumſtance, but every circumſtance in, or of Worſhip is not a Ceremony. A Ceremony is a circumſtance, and ſomething more. And a circumſtance may be made a Ceremony: <hi>ex. gr.</hi> The colour of a Beaſt offered in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was a circumſtance in it ſelf: But in the Heiſer of Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48221:3"/>the colour was ſpecified, and required to be Red, and no other: Here a circumſtance is made, more then naturally it was, a Ceremony. Say the ſame of <hi>Time. Place, Habit,</hi> &amp;c. abſtracted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered they were but circumſtances of Worſhip, but deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined or inſtituted by God were made Ceremonies, as were the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Feſtivals, Temple, Ephod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As for the Definition of a Ceremony (for a circumſtance is nothing but an Adjunct of any other thing, ſubſtance or action) it is variouſly given by divers Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; but all for the moſt part agree in this (even Heathens alſo in any Religion) <q>[That a Ceremony in Religion is a ſacred Rite inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uted for the honouring of God in his Publick Worſhip, and indeed a part of external Worſhip.]</q> The <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> cals them [Sacred myſtical Ceremonies, ſignificant ſymbolical Rites, <hi>Pag.</hi> 145.] Others call them <hi>Ritus colendi Deum;</hi> not only circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Rites to attend the Worſhip, but Rites of Worſhip: or Ceremonial, Ritual Worſhip: that is, parts of Worſhip: for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is divided into Moral and Ceremonial; which Diſtinction is idle and vain, if Ceremonies be not worſhip or parts of worſhip. The Learned <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> (and others) fearing this may fall foul upon our Ceremonies, have confounded Ceremonies with circumſtances, or at leaſt have equivocally uſed the words: For <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. He ſpeaks [of circumſtances properly ſo called, as time, place, habit, purely indifferent] in a general conſideration abſtractedly from Inconveniency; But he knowes that thoſe circumſtances determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God were made alſo Ceremonies: Inſtitution Divine made this alteration in, or gave this addition to them: And will not humane Inſtitution alſo of <hi>Sacred, myſtical, ſymbolical, ſignificant</hi> Rites do the ſame? That ſhall be tried hereafter. But in another place, <hi>Pag.</hi> 145. ſpeaking of ſuch Ceremonies, he confounds, or darkens the ſenſe by a Diſtinction: To this effect: [Ceremonies may be appointed to ſignifie the Favour of God, or the Grace of the Sacraments, or to be a means of receiving any Bleſſing from God, and this is very dangerous, if corrupt and ſuperſtitious men at any time rule the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—But if by Rights and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies we mean only the circumſtances of Divine worſhip, and by ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy that they are fitted to commend the Exerciſe, with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Decency to expreſs the Gravity and Devotion of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, I cannot diſcover ſo much danger.] But 1. Should not men ſpeak Properly in ſuch a controverſie as this, diſtinguiſhing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48221:3"/>Ceremonies from circumſtances? Do any that would be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, call meer circumſtances of Order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ceremonies? Are not natural and civil circumſtances ſo far ſignificant, to expreſs gravity and devotion, and tend to Edification, and yet no ſacred Ceremonies? 2. Though our Ceremonies do not ſignifie imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the favour of God, or the Grace of the Sacraments; yet do they ſignifie Duties on our part, Purity, Conſtancy, Humility: and unleſs they be idle and vain, (and for that cauſe be caſt out of Worſhip) they are intended to be a means of receiving ſome Bleſſing from God, by a moral operation of thoſe Graces and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties intended to be ſignified in their Inſtitution: And this will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily multiply their number, and in his Judgment render them dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, till (as he ſaith) they become ſtench in the Noſtrils of God, and of all ſober and ſtayd men] As in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> More of this hereafter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Inexpedient things.</hi>] This word had need to be explained; for it may have a double ſenſe. 1. Privatively, it is as much as <hi>not expedient:</hi> and ſo is the ſame almoſt with thoſe things the <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> cals <hi>purely Indifferent</hi> (of which in the next place) and often cals them Inconvenient. 2. Poſitively, as directly contrary to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, which ſignifies things <hi>uſeful, helpful</hi> in worſhip, or to the worſhip. He gives us this notion of them, when he ſaies, <hi>p.</hi> 49. [Ceremonies of the Church ought to be <hi>expedient</hi> not <hi>hurtful</hi> to the Church, not troubleſom to good Conſciences, not burdenſom] Things inexpedient therefore in worſhip are ſuch as are hurtful to the worſhip or worſhippers, troubleſom, burdenſom, in a word, any things that violate thoſe 7 Rules required in the Impoſition of Indifferent things in worſhip, <hi>Caſ.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 33. And in this ſenſe I think the Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> doth, or ſhould underſtand the word <hi>Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient;</hi> as a degree worſe then purely-indifferent (which alſo for their uſeleſſeneſs in worſhip are unlawfully impoſed by the Church or Magiſtrate, as we ſhall hear him aſſert anon) But yet (which is obſervable) in the proceſs of his Diſcourſe he confounds things inexpedient with things meerly or privatively incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, or unfit: The Inſtances are many, [<hi>Pag.</hi> 80. Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and inexpediency, <hi>Pag.</hi> 81. Any thing unfit and Inconvenient. <hi>Pag.</hi> 89. Inconvenience only. <hi>Pag.</hi> 91. An Inexpedient indifferent thing. <hi>Pag.</hi> 109. Somewhat inexpedient, barely inexpedient. <hi>Pag.</hi> 105.] But (under favour) this is either a tergiverſation, or perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48221:4"/>of the Queſtion; eſpecially in reſpect of the ſecond part, our ſubmiſſion to them: for though it be true that ſome things inconvenient ought not to be impoſed in worſhip, yet ſuch things if impoſed, may in ſome caſes be lawfully ſubmitted to, and in that No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion have been ſubmitted to, by ſome Learned and Pious Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts: For the Inconvenience may be only in a circumſtance of Worſhip, as at an unſeaſonable time, or unconvenient place, and the like. And if no other will be allowed, ſubmiſſion to them may be lawful, rather then not to enjoy the publick Ordinances. But if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient as Ceremonies, <hi>i. e,</hi> hurtful to the Worſhip as before; the Queſtion is altered, and ſome new Diſtinctions muſt be uſed, of which more perhaps hereafter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Things purely indifferent</hi>] What is meant by things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, he reſolved us in his firſt Caſe. A middle between neceſſary, as commanded, &amp; unlawful things, as forbidden; morally neither good nor bad in themſelves, but may be either by ſome circumſtance: And theſe ſeem to ſome to be of two ſorts. 1. Such as may be ſome circumſtance be made good or bad. 2. Such as when uſed in Worſhip, are at leaſt not good: (whether not bad is a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if Impoſed and uſed in Worſhip) Theſe our <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> cals purely Indifferent, others meerly Indifferent; or <hi>quatenus Indifferent. Caſe</hi> 6. What thoſe purely indifferent things are, he diſcovers not, either by a deſcription of them, or any one Inſtance in particular. Indeed at <hi>Caſe</hi> 12. He gives us the ſame deſcription of a thing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different (as at firſt) and applies it to a thing purely indifferent. [A middle place it holds between things <hi>neceſſary</hi> and things ſinful; between things expedient, and things inexpedient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in all regards purely indifferent.] And then tels us, [The Queſtion is not whether there be any ſuch things or no, but <hi>hoc ſuppoſito,</hi> that ſuch things there are, and that they are commanded by Lawful Authority] But did it not concern him to give one Inſtance of ſuch a thing as is <hi>purely Indifferent,</hi> not in its Nature and in it ſelf, for there are enough in that kind, but when Impoſed in Worſhip? That's the Caſe and Queſtion: [What's to be done by private perſons, when things purely indifferent are required in Religious Exerciſes?] Now if there be no ſuch things as purely Indifferent in worſhip, the Caſe is vain and idle: Speak Sir, to our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: Are our Ceremonies, as the <hi>Surplice,</hi> or <hi>Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm, a thing purely Indifferent in worſhip? You durſt not ſay ſo; for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48221:4"/>that had reflected upon the Church impoſing, as a crime, you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving formerly affirmed it unlawful to impoſe ſuch things upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral good Reaſons, <hi>Caſe</hi> 6. Therefore you had rather ſuppoſe ſuch a caſe ſhould be, then propoſe an Inſtance when it is ſo: <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè ſi non caſtè.</hi> But Sir, by things purely Indifferent, my ſelf, and ſome Readers underſtood you to mean things that were no way uſeful in worſhip, but like <hi>Herb-John</hi> in the Pot; if they do no good, they do no harm, as differencing them from things <hi>Inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi> as <hi>leſs evil.</hi> And this at laſt you give us to be the ſenſe, but when you thought this queſtion and your former ſenſe of it, <hi>Caſe</hi> 12. was forgotten, ſee <hi>Pag.</hi> 147. your own true deſcription of a thing purely indifferent, <hi>viz.</hi> [as to be of no uſe or ſervice] that is, in worſhip. Affirming [nothing ſo purely indifferent ought to be impoſed.] And in this ſenſe I take a thing purely indifferent in worſhip is a thing uſeleſs, needleſs, unneceſſary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in this notion if you do not take it, you will never fully reſolve the preſent Controverſie. As on the other ſide, if you take inexpedient only privatively, for not uſeful, or only inconvenient and unfit, your Caſes are coincident, if not the ſame; this of purely indifferent, and that of things inexpedient. But I paſs on in my Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>May be impoſed lawfully by men</hi>] This deſerves to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained a little. 1. To manifeſt where the Poyſon lies of moſt of humane Traditions applied to worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>Impoſers,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, only; alwaies, chiefly. For their Impoſition entrenches moſt upon the Wiſdom, and Soveraignty of God; and the Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, in appointing waies and meanes of his worſhip. 2. To diſtinguiſh between the Impoſers and Submitters in point of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. For ſome inconvenient things may lawfully be ſubmitted to, if they be impoſed, which may not but ſinfully be impoſed. As if a meer circumſtance unfit or inconvenient (in the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) be commanded in worſhip, without the Obſervation whereof, there can be no publick worſhip, it's granted by him to be unlawful to command ſuch a circumſtance, but ſtrongly pleaded to be lawful and expedient to obey it. 3. I adde, <hi>By men.</hi>] For God may by his Soveraignty command what indifferent, or to us ſeeming inconvenient things in worſhip, he pleaſes (as water in Baptiſm to ſignifie and operate the Grace of Regeneration) becauſe he hath power to work Grace by any means: but men as they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48221:5"/>have no Authority to inſtitute any <hi>means</hi> of Worſhip, ſo neither have they power to render them effectual to them that uſe them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>In the Worſhip of God.</hi>] For in civil things ther's a Latitude or Liberty both to Superiours to impoſe things inconvenient, or inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, both privatively, if not unfit; or poſitively, as hurtful; and for people to obey, without ſin: but not ſo generally in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: for there both may ſin, the one in commanding, the other in ſubmitting to unlawful things. Unlawful, I ſay, either in their own nature, or by ſome Accident or circumſtance becoming ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Worſhip. Of which hereafter more.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Or, if Impoſed, may lawfully be ſubmitted to.</hi>] This brings us to the ſecond queſtion, concerning Submiſſion to things inexpedient, or purely indifferent in Worſhip. For 1. That they may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be impoſed, is aſſerted often by the <hi>Caſuiſt.</hi> The ſubmiſſion to them is now conſiderable. 2. This ſubmiſſion may reſpect ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Miniſter who is to act them, by active obedience, or the People, who in ſome things are, or may be only paſſively obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, by preſence at them, when they are done without any aſſent or conſent unto them, yea with manifeſted diſſent from, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of them. Of which in another Place and Time.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Aſſented and Conſented unto.</hi>] And this leads us to the third and laſt queſtion. We have thus proceeded. 1. That ſome things inconvenient may not be impoſed in Worſhip. 2. That yet ſome ſuch things, if impoſed, may be barely ſubmitted to, and alſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in a Caſe. 3. We are now to go the laſt ſtep, whether they may be ſubmitted to with an unfeigned aſſent and conſent? The Explication is only here intended in three words. 1. <hi>Aſſent</hi>] hath reſpect to the <hi>truth</hi> of a thing, and is an act of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</hi> 2. <hi>Conſent</hi>] is an Act of the Will reſpecting the <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of a thing. 3. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned</hi>] implies the ſincerity and fulneſs of that Aſſent and Conſent from the bottom of the heart. The Terms of the queſtion being thus explained, we proceed to the Second thing propounded. How far Parties agree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>II. <hi>Poſtulata, ſive Conceſſa.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. Things uſed (or to be uſed) in Worſhip, are of three ſorts: <hi>Neceſſary, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> or of a <hi>middle ſort,</hi> of themſelves neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48221:5"/>good nor bad, but made ſo by circumſtances, called things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> as commanded by God: and they are of two ſorts. In ſpecial, as the particular Ordinances, the word and Sacraments. Or in general, as the neceſſary circumſtances tending to Decency, Order and Edification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 40. This Diſtinction is given us by the <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> in a little other terms, <hi>Caſe</hi> 12. <hi>Pag.</hi> 67. A thing is neceſſary either properly as expreſly commanded by God, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionarily, as expedient.] that is, with reſpect to the Rule of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and ſo generally commanded alſo. Things expedient then are Neceſſary in Worſhip by an occaſional or ſecondary Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; let that be remembred.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> or ſinful, from ſome Prohibition from God, and that (as was ſaid in the former) either in ſpecial, as forbidden by expreſs words, as Images in the Second Commandment: or in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and by conſequence, as all Imaginations and Inventions of men added to divine worſhip, which are prohibited in the negative part of the ſame Commandment: and alſo ſuch Circumſtances as are indecent, unorderly, and againſt Edification in the Negative part of that Precept, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. This Diſtinction is owned and given us alſo by the <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> in the ſame place, <hi>Pag.</hi> 68. A thing may be ſinful either in it ſelf, (that is, in its own Nature, as direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibited by God) or by ſome inconvenience in its uſe.] that is, when it is Inexpedient to be uſed in Worſhip; Inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as to the uſe, as he expreſſed himſelf there, <hi>pag.</hi> 66. Things Inexpedient then, as violating Order, Decency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Worſhip: Let this be remembred alſo againſt anon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Indifferent,</hi> of a middle ſort in themſelves neither good nor bad, as morally conſidered, or in their own Nature, but by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances they may become good or bad: or to uſe his own words [very apt by reaſon of Circumſtances to tend unto, to ſwerve unto, to become, or appear, either good or bad.] Now what thoſe Circumſtances are that change them into good or bad, he doth not thereby tell us (as he ought to have done) but yet we may collect his ſenſe or meaning, by what is already ſaid, (and more hereafter:) <hi>viz.</hi> they then become good, (yea neceſſary) when they are expedient for Decency, Order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Bad, <hi>i.e.</hi> ſinful when they are inconvenient, or inexpedient for thoſe ends, that is hurtful in their uſe.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48221:6"/>
               <p>For a Cloſe of the firſt Conceſſion, I ſhall only take and give notice of the <hi>Method</hi> of the <hi>Caſuiſt.</hi> In the former part treating of the <hi>Impoſition</hi> of things in Worſhip, he only denies the power to impoſe things, purely Indifferent, and Inexpedient, (ſuppoſing indeed that as Neceſſary things are commanded by God and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: ſo ſinful things may not be Impoſed by man.) but ſaies nothing of things <hi>doubtful</hi> or <hi>ſignificant,</hi> &amp;c But in the latter part, of <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> he inſtances in, and puts five Caſes, what is to be done, if ſuch things be impoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Neceſſary things. 2. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. 3. Purely Indifferent. 4. Inexpedient. 5. Sinful. In which Proceeding this is further obſervable, that he miſleads him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Reader by this gradation: as if all the 4 former were ſinleſs and lawful, and the laſt ſort only ſinful in Worſhip. But it already appears (by what hath already been ſaid, and will do more hereafter) that as the two firſt ſorts are only lawful in Worſhip, So the three laſt are all unlawful there; either in themſelves, as thoſe he cals ſinful, or by the Inconvenience of their uſe, as the third and fourth. And ſo ſtealing (in this Miſt) this Opinion, that things purely Indifferent or Inexpedient, without the former Diſtinction, are lawful in Worſhip: His Arguments for Submiſſion ſeem ſo Rational and Plauſible, taken from <hi>Peace, Duty, Safety.</hi> In a word, as he miſtakes, ſo he miſ-ſtates the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, diſputing for Submiſſion to things lawful in themſelves: when he ſhould prove things Inconvenient in their uſe, in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, may lawfully be ſubmitted to. This Obſervation being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred we thankfully accept this firſt Conceſſion, and proceed to the next.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nothing ſinful or unlawful, may be either Impoſed or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto in Divine Worſhip. 1. Not Impoſed: This needs no Proof, as confeſſed by all, that know what Religion is, and the Worſhip of God means. But we have the Aſſent and Conſent of our Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> often atteſted in this Point. For putting the Caſe, what is to be done, when things ſinful are Impoſed, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precates any [miſtake of being an Advocate for ſin or ſinful Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.] And preſently after reſolves, [ſuch Impoſitions are not to be obeyed,] and if not obeyed, to what end are they Impoſed? Yea when he reſolved before, that things purely Indifferent and Inexpedient cannot lawfully be Impoſed in Worſhip, much more will he deny things ſinful to be lawfully Impoſed. 2. Not Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48221:6"/>to if Impoſed. This is the Reſolution of the Caſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 119. peremptorily from the Authority of St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> and <hi>Bernard.</hi> [Things of themſelves and materially evil, as they cannot juſtly be commanded, ſo they cannot lawfully be done.] Yea in another Caſe. [What if they ſeem ſinful to us, though lawful in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if after ſincere and ſerious diſquiſition they ſeem ſtill ſinful to us?] He peremptorily concludes we muſt not obey, <hi>pag.</hi> 126. Much leſs if it be ſinful in it ſelf. But ſeeing ſome things are ſinful, not materially or in themſelves, but in their uſe, what will he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve in the latter caſe? Whether may ſuch things be Impoſed in Worſhip: or if Impoſed, be ſubmitted to? The Reſolution of this ſully and clearly would have put an end to the preſent Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; But he either waves it, or obſcures it. Yet ſomething ſhall be ſaid to it in the next Conceſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No Inexpedient thing may lawfully be impoſed in worſhip,
<note place="margin">See <hi>pag.</hi> 69. Ther's a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Authority to Impoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is expedient in the Worſhip of God, and <hi>p.</hi> 73. admits the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erting of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in requiring of things that are lawful, but inexpedient, to be unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> or ſubmitted to. 1. Not impoſed: this is fully yielded us, <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>Caſe</hi> 8. [It being againſt the Rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>(all things are not expedient)</hi> and indeed againſt common Reaſon; it is not lawful in Church-Governours to impoſe any thing about Gods worſhip that is only Indifferent, and lawful in its ſelf, but not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.] Had he given us his Reaſons againſt Impoſition of ſuch things in worſhip (as he doth in things purely Indifferent) he had done noble ſervice to the Church; yet ſomething he hinted in the words alledged [Its againſt the Apoſtles Rule, and common Reaſon to impoſe ſuch things,] and more explicitly in the words afore theſe immediately [All things that are Indifferent and not expedient, are not lawful, but ſinful] Sinful! Surely he muſt not mean materially and in themſelves (for they were not then Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent) but ſinful in their uſe if Impoſed or uſed in Worſhip: that is, becauſe they are Inexpedient, yea hurtful to the Worſhip, againſt Order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to the Worſhippers too often. In a word, againſt the Second Commandment. 2 Not ſubmitted to. For this we have his Aſſent alſo. <hi>[Things not expedient to be done) ought not to be done,</hi> and things not expedient to be commanded, ought not to be commanded.] Where we have both aſſerted. They ought not to be impoſed, or if impoſed, not ſubmitted to. If he, or any for him ſhall ſay (as ſome for him do ſay) things not expedient, if left free to our choyce, may not be done, but if commanded, that alters the Caſe. I Anſwer (though I think he intended not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48221:7"/>this hidden ſenſe in this place) 1. He hath aſſerted that [things not expedient (in worſhip) are not lawful, but ſinful] as afore. And can the Command of Authority make that lawful which, if not in it ſelf, yet in its uſe is ſinful? 2. It is acknowledged by a Proſelyte, and ſtout Advocate of the <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> [That if the things be ſinful, they may neither be lawfully Impoſed nor Submitted to.] I ſee his Evaſion: He meanes if they be ſinful in themſelves, or in their Nature, and not if only ſinfully commanded. But I rejoyn. Things may be ſinful in their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> as inexpedient (as was ſaid and granted by his Freind, <hi>ſupra</hi> Conceſſion. 1.) and will he, dare he affirm, that things either way ſinful, may be either impoſed, or practiſed in Worſhip? I believe he will not upon ſecond and ſerious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nothing purely Indifferent (that is idle, or of no uſe) in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Pag.</hi> 147. Nothing pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indifferent ought to be Impoſed, as all moderate men allow.</note> may be impoſed in worſhip, or if impoſed, ſubmitted to in Practiſe. 1. Not impoſed, that's granted, and aſſerted often. Firſt, he hath a caſe wholly againſt it, <hi>Caſe</hi> 6. Where, by ſeveral Arguments he confutes that Opinion; ſome whereof are taken from the groſs <hi>Abſurdities</hi> which would follow if ſuch a power were granted to Church-Governours. All <hi>a poſteriori,</hi> only the laſt <hi>a priori.</hi> God hath not inveſted them with ſuch a power, which though I grant to be true, ſome of his good Friends will not allow him: For they ſay God hath not only given allowance, but a Command to the Church-Rulers, to ordain Ceremonies for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Decency, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. Yes, may he ſay, but not what indifferent things they pleaſe. But according to the Rules of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Scripture: that they be few and wholſom, expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I pray who ſhall be Judge of their Impoſitions? If themſelves only in their Prudence and Diſcretion, they may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what, and as many as they pleaſe. And though the Rev. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuist</hi> ſaies, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. [he never met with any high Conformiſt that allowed them ſuch a power,] yet ſure he forgot himſelf. For a few Leaves after, <hi>pag.</hi> 36. he brings in the great and famous Defender of this Church, confidently, and expreſly aſſerting ſuch a Power. <q>[Church-Governours (ſaith he) have liberty to eſtabliſh what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever being in it ſelf indifferent, ſhall to their wiſdom ſeem moſt expedient.]</q> But let that paſs. How doth he prove [that God hath not inve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed them with ſuch an Arbitrary and ſtrangely unlimited power?] Not a word to prove it, which concerned him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48221:7"/>to have done; ſeeing others affirm, that he hath ſuch a Power. One Argument <hi>a priore,</hi> from the Prohibition of God, had done the deed. That was, the ſinfulneſs of ſuch things in Worſhip. Why? Becauſe they are either againſt the Apoſtles Rule, (they are againſt (or not according to) Order, Decency, or Edification.) or againſt the Third Commandment of the firſt Table, (the general Rule of worſhip) as idle, uſeleſs, ſuperfluous, and conſequently a taking of Gods Name in vain. Again he tels us, what he had told us before, that [ſuch things, <hi>viz.</hi> purely Indifferent, ought not to be enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Authority.] 2. But what if they be Impoſed? May they be ſubmitted to by Miniſters, or People? For this, he is as peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory for the Affirmative, as he was before for the Negative. <q>[When a thing is once required, though not expedient as we would deſire (here he cals things purely indifferent not Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) we are under an obligation, and we muſt not conſult our Liberty, but our Duty. Not ſo much our liberty to forbear, as our liberty to obey,</q> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 69.] And preſently endeavours to prove this his Aſſertion <q>[By three things of ſo great concern, and even indiſpenſable conveniency, that the ordinary inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of any lawful thing enjoyned, ſeems very light and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, <hi>&amp;c. pag</hi> 90 and they are Peace, Duty, Safety.]</q> But (let it be obſerved) This he could not affirm, till firſt he had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſtate of the Queſtion: which was of things not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, or Inexpedient, turning the ſenſe into Unfit and Inconvenient. And 2. Pittifully begged the queſtion; that the things ſpecified, (whether purely indifferent, or inexpedient) are lawful in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. He muſt not mean lawful in themſelves, or in their nature, but alſo in their uſe in worſhip. For this Diſtinction he gave us, (and we ſhall hold him to it) in the firſt Conceſſion: <q>[A thing may be ſinful either in it ſelf,</q> or by the inconveniency of its uſe] that is, when it is inexpedient to be uſed in worſhip. A thing therefore may be lawful in it ſelf, out of worſhip; which may be ſinful by the inconvenience of its uſe, if uſed in worſhip. And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this groſs (I ſay not prevarication, for I judge reverently of the <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> he intended not to pervert the ſtate of the queſtion, but) miſtake or ſlip of his Judgment or Memory, the whole fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe is founded. He ſuppoſes (and it hath miſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d too many) that becauſe the things are lawful in themſelves, abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from worſhip, therefore though inconvenient in worſhip; they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48221:8"/>may be lawfully obeyed in worſhip, and yet ſinfully impoſed. And this Miſtake I confeſs he might the more eaſily fall upon, by the non-obſervation of a double Diſtinction, uſeful to the deciſion of this Controverſie. 1. Between the Nature of the things inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient impoſed in worſhip. They are either meer Circumſtances, or more even Religious Ceremonies; If the firſt be impoſed (though ſinfully by Authority) rather then loſe the ſubſtance of Worſhip, the Ordinances of God, they may, yea muſt be ſubmitted to, and obeyed. But if they be Sacred Ceremonies of humane Invention, and Inſtitution, they may not (I yet think) be obeyed; at leaſt, that's the queſtion. 2. Ther's another Diſtinction to be obſerv'd between Active and Paſſive Obedience, when ſuch things are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. It may be lawful (as I yet ſuppoſe, to prevent ſeparation from a Church) to yield Paſſive Obedience, by preſence at the Ordinances, when not to be had without them, having ſhewed our diſlike and diſſent. But the queſtion is of Active Obedience in acting thoſe Impoſitions, which involves our aſſent and conſent, either unfeigned or hypocritical. But I return to the Rev. <hi>Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt</hi> And had he not in his Title Page, limited his Diſcourſe to <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> Matters, that is, Matters of Divine worſhip, I ſhould have ſuggeſted another Diſtinction, between Civil and Sacred Affairs, with reſpect to the power of Superiours in both of theſe. It may give a little light to the buſineſs in hand, and therefore I ſhall briefly touch it. In civil affairs the ſupream Authority may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome things inconvenient, or inexpedient, that is perhaps hurtful to the buſineſs, and to the Subjects or Inferiours, and muſt alſo be obeyed; But in Religion and Worſhip, as he may impoſe nothing inexpedient (as is granted above) ſo if he doth impoſe ſuch things in worſhip (with the Limitations and former Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) he is not to be obeyed. And this I ſhall briefly make good againſt him by his own Principles, and Conceſſions, and other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 1. No ſinful or unlawful thing may be (impoſed or) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to in worſhip: but things inconvenient in their uſe, are ſinful: See the firſt Conceſſion, <hi>Paragr.</hi> 2. <q>[A thing may be ſinful either in it ſelf,</q> or by the inconvenience of its uſe, <hi>p</hi> 68.] Therefore they may not be ſubmitted to. 2 No inexpedient thing may be (impoſed or) ſubmitted to in worſhip: This is yielded in the third Conceſſion; and the Reaſon is, becauſe they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. So he affirmed afore, <hi>pag.</hi> 35, 36. <q>[All things that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48221:8"/>and not expedient, are not lawful but ſinful.]</q> But things purely indifferent are inexpedient in worſhip. This is alſo his own Expreſſion, now he is ſpeaking of things purely indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, to call them inconvenient, not expedient; And ſurely he will not deny but purely Indifferent things impoſed in worſhip, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient in their uſe, and not expedient or inexpedient. (If he take theſe terms for the ſame) therefore not to be ſubmitted to.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No things that cauſe the ſubmitter to them, to prophane the worſhip of God, by taking his Name in vain, againſt the Third Commandment, are to be ſubmitted to, though they be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; this cannot with any Reaſon be denied: But purely indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things, that is, (by his own Expoſition) ſuch as are of no uſe in Service or worſhip, but idle, uſeleſs, ſuperfluous, (perhaps ridiculous) do prophane the Worſhip of God, therefore they are not to be ſubmitted to.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nothing that violates the Rule of the Apoſtle concerning Order, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cency and Edification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. ought to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or if impoſed, ſubmitted to; That ſuch things may not be impoſed, is aſſerted ſtrongly, <hi>pag.</hi> 43. <q>[Nothing that is diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, indecent, (or againſt Edification in Gods Worſhip, can warrantably be impoſed upon the Church.]</q> But things purely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different (deſcribed as afore) are indecent, diſorderly, and unedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying in Worſhip; <hi>ergo</hi> not to be impoſed, and for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be ſubmitted to, becauſe they are ſinful againſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Precept: Much more might be added, but I forbear till we come to the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> in our Ceremonies. I have been large in this, I ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhorter in the next Conceſſions.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Nothing really ſuperſtitious may be impoſed in worſhip, or if impoſed, ſubmitted to. 1. Not impoſed: For that's a manifeſt injury to, and violation (as of the whole firſt Table of the Decalogue in general, ſo) of the Second Commandment thereof in ſpecial, which forbids all ſuperſtitious Worſhip, as falſe. Our Rev. <hi>Caſuist</hi> ſpeaks not expreſly of this Caſe, in regard of the Impoſition of ſuch things; but comprehends it (as I ſuppoſe) under the general of things ſinful and unlawful, and that is enough againſt the Impoſition of them. 2. And as for ſubmiſſion to them, he ſeems to grant that if the things be proved to be really ſuch (as by ſome they are ſuppoſed to be) they need not, they ought not to be ſubmitted to. To diſcover his Judgment herein he puts a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48221:9"/>caſe [wherein doth Superſtition, or the appearance thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt? <hi>pag.</hi> 129. And he reduces all to 4 Heads. 1. <hi>Merit.</hi> 2. <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> 3. <hi>Perfection.</hi> 4. <hi>Neceſſity</hi>] Whether all the kinds of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition fall under theſe 4 heads, I am not fully ſatisfied: But he ſeems to me to grant, that if they be truly and really ſuperſtitious, we may lawfully diſobey the Impoſition of them. But of this more in <hi>Hypotheſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Nothing doubtful or ſuſpicious of ſinfulneſs ought to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in worſhip, or if impoſed, ſubmitted to. For the Impoſition of ſuch things in the worſhip of God the Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> ſaies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or but little directly, as not making it a diſputable Caſe; only by conſequence he ſaies ſomething to it in another Caſe. [What is to be done when a thing ſeems ſinful to us?] And he ſeems to reſolve it negatively, we ought not to ſubmit unto it. For <hi>pag.</hi> 124. He thus beſpeakes his private perſon. [If thy diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for ſatisfaction, hath brought thee to this, that thou art in a doubt, whether thou maiſt obey or no, firſt I recommend thee to that excellent <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> the Rev. B. of <hi>Lincolne.]</hi> But what if he ſatisfie him not; then hear his own Reſolution, <hi>pag.</hi> 126. [If the thing required appear ſinful to thee ſtill, thou art bound by the Law, thou art bound to the peace of thine own Conſcience,—Thou maiſt not obey.] Thence would I infer if in doubtful things, I am not bound to obey (for if I doubt, and do a thing, eſpecially in worſhip, I ſin) the Magiſtrate ſeems pre-obliged not to command ſuch things: For to what end, if the doubtful need not, muſt not obey him? But of this alſo more in <hi>Hypotheſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. No <hi>part of worſhip</hi> may be impoſed in Divine Service by men. The Reaſon is given by the Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> twice, becauſe it is ſuperſtitious; once <hi>p.</hi> 4. and 130. Adding, It's Gods Prerogative alone to preſcribe his own Worſhip; <hi>Command.</hi> 2. and forbidden to men in the Negative part thereof.</p>
               <p n="8">8. No ſignificant thing (or Ceremony) may by men be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Worſhip.] The Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> having propounded this caſe, <hi>p.</hi> 144. [Whether the imputing of ſignificancy to things impoſed render them ſuperſtitious?] Reſolves the Caſe by a double or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther treble Diſtinction. 1. Of Ceremonies from Circumſtances of Worſhip. 2. Of the Authors or Inſtitutors of Worſhip, God or Men. 3. Of Significancy, to ſignifie either the Favour of God, the Grace of the Sacraments, or to be a meanes of receiving any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48221:9"/>Bleſſing from God, or to intend only fitneſs to commend the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe with Order and Decency, and to expreſs the gravity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of the Worſhippers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] The Reſult is this, That <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> (not meer Circumſtances) inſtituted by men (not God) ſignifying the Favour of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (not Order, Decency, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) are very dangerous, if corrupt and ſuperſtitious men ſhould at any time rule the Church: and we may have quickly not 7, but 70 times 7 if not entire, yet Semi-Sacraments, the Church of God and his Service being thereby obnoxious to all the antick and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Crotchets that the vain imaginations of over-curious men can cumber them with, till they become ſtench in the Noſtrils of all ſober and ſtayd men, and of God himſelf, as with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>] This is enough to decide the Controverſie in hand, if juſtly appliable to our Ceremonies. To the Conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we now proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>III. <hi>The Proof of the Negative in all the Particulars.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hitherto following the ſteps of the Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded only <hi>in Theſi,</hi> concerning things Inexpedient, or purely Indifferent, whether they may be impoſed, or if impoſed, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to in worſhip; and have gathered his Conceſſions into one view, and ſhewed how far both Parties agree: We are now come to the Application of theſe Conceſſions <hi>in Hypotheſi.</hi> to the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our bitter Contentions at this day: And much of my work is done already. The Propoſitions being granted me, and proved, I ſhall need only to prove the <hi>Aſſumptions</hi> of all my Syllogiſmes:</p>
               <p>For if our Ceremonies prove ſuch things, as the Conceſſions grant, the Concluſions will eaſily follow, that they are unlawful, to be either Impoſed in Worſhip, or Submitted to: I ſhall now therefore ſtate the Queſtion anew in our particular Caſe, thus:</p>
               <q>Whether our Ceremonies may lawfully by men be Impoſed in the Worſhip of God: or, if Impoſed, may lawfully be Submitted, Aſſented and Conſented unto?</q>
               <p>The Explication of the Terms is laid down in the beginning, and the Probleme containes 3 queſtions, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the Lawfulneſs 1. Of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48221:10"/>the Impoſition of them in worſhip. 2. Of the Submiſſion to them. 3. Of the Declaration of an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. To the Particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>I. <hi>Of the Impoſition of Ceremonies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What we, and moſt Learned Divines underſtand by a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impoſed in worſhip, was diſcourſed in the Explicatory part at the Entrance of this Diſſertation, <hi>viz.</hi> a Sacred Rite of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God intended and inſtituted to the honouring God in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; whereby it is contra-diſtinguiſhed to a meer Circumſtance of Worſhip, tending to Decency, Order and Edification. Now that ſuch Ceremonies may not be Impoſed, the Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> doth not explicitly aſſert (that had been dangerous to himſelf) but yet implicitly inſinuates ſo much: [If Ceremonies ſignificant of the Grace and Favour of God, or to be a meanes of receiving any Bleſſing from God be impoſed, there is, no doubt, (ſaies he) much danger in it, <hi>p</hi> 145.] But what if meer Circumſtances be impoſed? But of this more in that Head of <hi>Significancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it is unlawful for the Church or Magiſtrate to impoſe our Ceremonies, will appear by Application of all or moſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions above, given us by the Reverend <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> himſelf; In Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral thus. No ſinful, unlawful thing may by any ſort of men be impoſed in worſhip. This is yielded by all of any Religion, as at Conceſſion 2. But I aſſume, our Ceremonies impoſed are ſinful and unlawful; <hi>ergo</hi> they ought not to be impoſed in Worſhip: The Aſſumption is proved by the ſpecial Conceſſions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. [All things impoſed or uſed in Worſhip, are either neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or unlawful; and ſo either Good or Bad: But our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are not neceſſary; <hi>ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is conſtantly and frequently affirmed by the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates thereof. God was, is, and may be well, yea better ſerved without them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is granted in the firſt Conceſſion. Neceſſary a commanded by God; ſpecially, or generally. Unlawful, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God, either in ſpecial or in general. If it be ſaid, but there are ſome things Indifferent, neither commanded, nor forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by God, as the Diviſion above was Tripartite. I Anſwer, There are three things in themſelves abſtractedly conſidered which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48221:10"/>are Indifferent, neither morally good nor bad; but in Worſhip, nothing Impoſed is Indifferent, but it is either expedient for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Order, and ſo commanded and neceſſary; or Inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in the uſe, and ſo forbidden and unlawful; It is aſſerted by our <hi>Caſuiſt, Caſe</hi> 2. [No one Action (he might have added, no Ceremony) in Religious Exerciſes is of its own nature ſo Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but that by the Circumſtances, it eaſily becomes good or evil.] Good, if it be expedient in, or uſeful to the Worſhip: evil, if any waies Inconvenient in its uſe, that is, Inexpedient, or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Worſhip. Of this more in the next.</p>
               <p n="2">2. [Nothing Inexpedient may be impoſed in Worſhip: but ſuch are our Ceremonies; <hi>ergo</hi> &amp;c.] The <hi>Major</hi> is fully conceded above, and proved alſo by very good Reaſons; this for one, [All things indifferent and not expedient, are not lawful but ſinful.] If not expedient things, that is, not uſeful to the worſhip, be ſinful, then much more, things inexpedient that is, hurtful to the worſhip, are ſinful: In the Explication of this Term, <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> it was ſhewed, that as, <hi>Expedient,</hi> imports ſomething poſitive, uſeful, helpful to the worſhip; ſo, <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> muſt (in the juſt oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſignifie ſomething prejudicious, hurtful to it: Not <hi>privative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> only, which may be taken for ſome things purely Indifferent; but poſitively, as hurtful, troubleſome, burdenſome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Minor,</hi> that the Ceremonies in Controverſie, are <hi>inexpedient</hi> and hurtful to the worſhip, or worſhippers, is abundantly proved by others, and evident by Experience: as violating moſt of his 7 Rules, given for regulating the Impoſition of Indifferent things in worſhip, <hi>Caſe</hi> 8. Take the Particulars briefly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. [They break the Peace of the Church, which ought prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be regarded in Impoſition of ſuch things.] The <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> proceeds excellently and boldly in the Vindication of his ſecond Rule for Publick Peace. I wiſh the Impoſers of our Ceremonies would read or hear his words, and ſeriouſly lay them to heart. [God is the God of Peace and Order, of Peace as well as Order. And as the Order, ſo the Peace of the Church (without which, there is no Order) is precious with him, and with all that have the Spirit of God, and any care of his Church: Should any thing give way to Peace, and ſhould not things Indifferent? Are not theſe Indifferent? Is not Peace neceſſary in many reſpects?] See the Place. Who knows not, that as the firſt Breach of the Publick
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48221:11"/>Peace of the Church, was about a Ceremony, or thing Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; ſo theſe Ceremonies impoſed have for many years broken the peace of our Church, and now worſt of all? I ſhall add a few more of the Reverend <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> words. [Who can think it wiſdom to force any thing that is but indifferent, to the endangering ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a thing as peace, or the dividing of the Church of God, or provoking any conſiderable part thereof to ſeparate from us?] But I forbear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are offenſive to weak Brethren [who (as he well) though weak, are not to be thrown to the wals, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, yea the Scripture reaſons us to a greater tenderneſs to the weaker part of the Church.] And more to this purpoſe. Things inexpedient of this nature are deſcribed by our Rev. <hi>Caſuist,</hi> to be ſuch as are troubleſom to good Conſciences, burdenſom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, Ceremonies of the Church ought not to be hurtful to the Church, troubleſom, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 49. The Apoſtles had a ſpecial care of this, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not to trouble <hi>Gentile</hi> Believers with <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.19. And how much trouble and ſad diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons theſe Ceremonies have brought upon many truly tender Conſciences, is too viſible. While they were put upon this <hi>Rack,</hi> either to violate the peace of their Conſciences, or to run upon their utter undoing by the rigour of the Law. I commend to their Conſideration a Speech of Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> to be ſeen. <hi>p.</hi> 40. (a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Defender of Ceremonies.) [He that in things indifferent hath not a tender care of weak Chriſtians, ſheweth that there is not that Charity in him, nor regard of his Brethren which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.] But I pray Sir, Ought there not to be the ſame tender care of weak Chriſtians, after they are commanded? Let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The next Rule violated, to render them inexpedient, is [that of Edification; the grand Level of all Church-power (ſaith our Author) Edification, and not its Deſtruction, in the whole or in any part. The great Principle of ſuch Impoſitions muſt be Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, not envy at, or deſire of revenge, upon any perſon or party otherwiſe minded. Not to ſhew victory over them, or dominion over their Faith or Actions.] Add the next words, with a very little variation. [Things I doubt, not ſincerely abhorred by our preſent Governours, as nor by our former] Things then that make not for Edification, but rather againſt it, ought not to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48221:11"/>in worſhip; becauſe they are inexpedient, either privative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as not furthering Edification, or poſitively, as hindering or hurting it. But our Ceremonies, and other Impoſitions do rather hinder, then further Edification; and by Edification I mean true ſpiritual Edification, not carnal or ſuperſtitious; there are ſome things, that in (<hi>Tertullians</hi> Language) do <hi>aedificare ad Gehennam;</hi> edifie downwards, or to deſtruction; that is, to take men off from the power of Godlineſs, and make them <hi>formal,</hi> placing all their Relig on in Ceremonies, and Ceremonious Worſhip; as it was with the old Papiſts, the Phariſees, and at this day with the new Phariſees the Papiſts; yea they have turned to the deſtruction of precious Miniſters, and pious people. I need ſay no more to that.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The next is, That they violate [that moſt noble Rule of all, that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> A ſtanding Rule (as he goes on) never to be croſſed by any Authority under Heaven: yea God himſelf will never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe it. Then (ſaies he) nothing that is indecent, or diſorderly in Gods Worſhip, can warrantably be Impoſed upon the Church.] Now how diſorderly ſome things impoſed in our Liturgy are, the Reverend Commiſſioners, and others have manifeſted. And if men were not reſolved upon their own Inventions: Is not Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Lords Supper a diſorderly Geſture? Not only varying from the firſt Pattern, but from the Order of all Nations, who ſtand or ſit, but never kneel at a Supper? and as contrary to the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the prime or pureſt Churches for the firſt 600 years together; who by the Decrees of Councils, forbad Kneeling at Prayer, on all Lords daies? And <hi>Custom</hi> is one of the Rules of Impoſition given by the <hi>Caſuiſt.</hi> [Of very great uſe to indicate what is decent and orderly: Cuſtom is Umpire of Indifferent things, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 44] I might have made this a diſtinct Head by it ſelf, But it may ſuffice to touch at it here.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The laſt <hi>Rule</hi> violated by humane Ceremonies impoſed in Worſhip is, <hi>Goſpel</hi> or <hi>Christian-Liberty.</hi> [This muſt not be inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any Impoſition which is infringed, if theſe and other rules be not obſerved. 1. If any thing indifferent be impoſed, which any way checketh with the former Rules of Expediency, Peace, Offence of the weak, Edification, Decency, Order, and the Cuſtom of the Churches. 2. If things indifferent be required
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48221:12"/>with equal ſeverity as things neceſſary.] I liſt not to make the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. How far theſe Rules are infringed in the Impoſition of our Ceremonies, he that runs may read it. By what hath been ſaid already, they are now ſufficiently proved to be in inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and hurtful to the Worſhip and Worſhippers, and therefore ought not to be Impoſed in our Worſhip. But further.</p>
               <p n="3">3 [Nothing purely Indifferent ought to be Impoſed in Worſhip. This Propoſition is fully yielded, aſſerted and proved above at the fourth Conceſſion. The Aſſumption, That our Ceremonies are ſuch, <hi>i. e.</hi> purely Indifferent, will be manifeſted from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a thing <hi>Purely Indifferent,</hi> given us by the Reverend <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> above in the Explication. <hi>[A thing ſo Indifferent as to be of no uſe, or Service (in Worſhip) not more Expedient then Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.]</hi> that is, (as I ſuppoſe) neither good nor bad. But I queſtion whether any thing Impoſed in worſhip is not either good or bad: yea therefore bad, becauſe it is not good. The ſenſe is Things purely Indifferent, are things uſeleſs, needleſs, idle, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, the Worſhip being compleat and perfect without them; Now it is confeſt by all that our Ceremonies are not neceſſary (as was ſaid above) but yet their <hi>uſefulneſs</hi> is ſtrongly pleaded for, as decent and orderly, adding Beauty and Luſtre to the Worſhip: I could ask many Queſtions here. 1 Are not Gods Ordinances orderly and decent without them? If not, they charge the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, as not able to manage his Worſhip decently and orderly without the help of fooliſh men. If ſo, what need have they of a <hi>painted Beauty,</hi> having a native beauty of their own? 2. To whom do Ceremonies ſeem to add Decency and Order to Divine Ordinances? Not to God, or truly Devout Chriſtians, who are both beſt pleaſed with the ſimplicity of Gods preſcribed Worſhip. To whom then I will not ſay. 4. What Decency, or Order is there is a <hi>Surplice,</hi> more then in a Gown, or Cloak (ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> wore) but of ſome mens fancying? 4. If they plead them uſeful as ſignificant Rites, to excite Devotion, or Duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall therefore plead them <hi>uſeleſs,</hi> needleſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe what is expected by them, is done before, and better, by the Ordinances themſelves. Of which more upon another account.</p>
               <p n="4">4. [Nothing really ſuperſtitious (or eaſily abuſed to Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) may be Impoſed in Worſhip. But our Ceremonies are guilty of Superſtition, and ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed, not only at <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48221:12"/>but by many amongſt our ſelves; <hi>ergo,</hi> &amp;c.] The firſt Propoſition was the fifth Conceſſion: but lightly touched, intended to be more largely handled here. Thus the Rev. <hi>Caſuist</hi> ſpeakes more fully. [Upon ſuppoſition that the Idolatry, or ſuperſtition (and ſuperſtition is a degree of Idolatry) cannot be ſevered from the uſe of a thing, or very hardly done; Idolatry and Superſtition muſt have no Indulgence: the Serpent it ſelf muſt be broken in pieces; and that famous Rule of Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> is applauded by all,] See <hi>pag.</hi> 141. (The rather becauſe it is the Teſtimony of a Pope againſt his Succeſſors) the words are theſe. [If ſome of our Predeceſſors have done ſome things which at that time might be without fault, and afterwards are turned into Errour and Superſtition, without any delay, and with great Authority, they may be deſtroyed by Poſterity.] But Superſtition being not in the things uſed, or requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but in the perſons that ſuperſtitiouſly require, or uſe them, grounded in the falſe Doctrine, and Superſtitious Opinion which perſons have of them, how ſhall we come to know when things are ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed? And then how can we charge our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies with Superſtition? Our Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> hath given us ſome rules to try them by, <hi>pag.</hi> 130, &amp;c. which we ſhall apply to the caſe in hand as we go. Only premiſing theſe two things. 1. That we li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not our Diſcourſe only to the 3 Ceremonies, <hi>Surplice, Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Kneeling,</hi> but enlarge it to any other Rites and Ceremonies Impoſed and uſed in the Publick Worſhip; even to the Liturgy it ſelf, which being the <hi>Form</hi> of divine Service, as it is called, may be ſtiled, a <hi>Grand Ceremony.</hi> 2. That it muſt not be expected that all the Rules of Diſcovery ſhould be applied to every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Ceremony to prove it ſuperſtitious; but any one may ſuffice, if rightly applied. And now I proceed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt way of Diſcovery of <hi>Superſtition</hi> is by the 4 Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters thereof given by Learned Divines. An Opinion of Merit; of Worſhip; of Perfection; of Neceſſity. Any one of theſe found in our Ceremonies will teſtifie the perſons that ſo uſe them to be Superſtitious.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Merit.</hi> [When (to take his own words) we think God is bound to reward our Inventions, and that by our Purſes or Labours we purchaſe his favour, this is Superſtition.] And does not a great <hi>Rabbi</hi> of our Church (whoſe Learning and Books are not only applauded, and admired as <hi>Oracles,</hi> but approved as Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48221:13"/>by our Rulers,) profeſs openly and confidently. [It is his Doctrine that <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> (his <hi>Free-will-Offerings</hi>) are more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, more acceptable, and more rewardable with God then commanded Duties.] Amongſt which Free will Oblations, the <hi>Liturgy</hi> is one, great one, the only Form of Divine Service, as it is called by ſome; and do not the vulgar and many higher perſons eſteem it to be moſt commendable, moſt acceptable, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently moſt rewardable Service of God? and if not with their Purſes, yet by the labour of their Lips; in bearing a part in that Service, to purchaſe his Favour? And is not this Superſtition? If it be rewardable, it muſt be either by ſome Promiſe, but there is none ſuch in Scripture. Or of due Debt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. but that is plain Merit; there's no third way to ground the Reward on.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of <hi>Worſhip.</hi> [When things are required as parts, or of the Eſſence of Divine Worſhip, or ſo uſed, this is Superſtition] But the <hi>Liturgy</hi> it ſelf is by the Rulers made and called the Form of Divine Worſhip, not a part only, but the whole Eſſence and Subſtance thereof. 2. Ceremonies are eſteemed by all Religions, Rites of Worſhip, Ceremonial worſhip, and ſo parts of worſhip, (as was proved above.) 3. They are made by the Impoſers, <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> not civil Ceremonies, and ſo parts of Religion, that is, of Worſhip, and ſo uſed by many: Certainly Kneeling at Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a part of external worſhip, and ſo eſteemed and uſed by moſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Of <hi>Perfection.</hi> [When we conceive the true Beauty of the Church, and the Perfection of Chriſtianity conſiſteth in things of humane Invention. This is Superſtition.] And do not ſome, on this ſide <hi>Rome,</hi> place the Perfection of Chriſtianity, and the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion, in Pompous Ceremonies, Glorious Temples, Sweet and melodious Muſick, Gawdy Prieſtly Garments, a compleated Liturgy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And do not many think the Service <hi>undecent</hi> without a Surplice? the Baptiſm <hi>imperfect</hi> without the Croſs? the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>irreverently</hi> received without Kneeling? Is not this groſs ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Of <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> [When ſuch things are required, and ſo uſed, as ſimply neceſſary in their Nature, being but things Indifferent. This is alſo Superſtition.] And I pray, hath not a Learned Doctor a Late Biſhop, pleaded the Liturgy to be ſo neceſſary, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, there can be no Religion, no honeſty, no Allegiance. And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48221:13"/>do not the Late Commiſſioners plead a Precept of Scripture for their Ceremonies? Not an Allowance only, but a Command to inſtitute Ceremonies? And is not that neceſſary? In a word, does not the Late Act make them ſo neceſſary (as far as they can) that the commanded worſhip muſt rather be omitted, then any of their humane divine Service omitted? that men muſt not worſhip God without obſervation of their Ceremonies? Wear a Surplice, or pray not, preach not: Croſs the Child, or baptize not: Kneel, or receive not the other Sacrament. And for the ordinary uſers of them, it is obſervable, that humane Inventions added to the Worſhip of God, as they are more ſtrictly obſerved then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Worſhip of God, <hi>Micah</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> ſo after long continuance, they are eſteemed neceſſary; as (falſly) ſuppoſed to be of Divine Original. Theſe are the ordinary Characters of Superſtition, which I could wiſh were not too viſible ſpots in the face of our Church; But I believe there are more and other waies to diſcover Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then theſe. As, 1. To put Holineſs in things, times, places. 2. To put vertue, efficacy, in things which they have not neither in their Natures, nor by Divine Inſtitution. 3. To put ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon Ceremonies in Divine Worſhip. Of which more by and by.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next Rule is [when upon evident and undeniable grounds of General Practiſe, it appears to the ſober and unbyaſſed ſort of men, that a thing is uſed ſuperſtitiouſly in any of the former Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, then no doubt there is an appearance of Superſtition.] Now firſt the Cenerality of our Nation, are proved afore, to be ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the uſe of our Liturgy and Ceremonies. And for the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that conform to them ſome are known to be Popiſhly ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; in Bowing, Croſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some are by aſſed by Profits or Preferments that are gotten or loſt thereby. Only ſome few Sober, Learned and unbyaſſed perſons are free from the guilt of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: ſticking to the ſimplicity of Goſpel-worſhip.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third Rule given, and moſt undoubted, is [Look to the Doctrine of the Church, whence the Grounds of Impoſition and Practiſe are drawn: If they be falſe and ſuperſtitious, then there is an appearance of evil to be avoyded.] We joyn iſſue in this alſo, and apply it to the Caſe in hand.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Doctrine of the Church though found in moſt of the 39 Articles, hath yet been ſcrupled at by Nonconformiſts in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48221:14"/>Inſtitution of Ceremonies; and the Doctrine and Power given queſtioned: [The Church hath power to Impoſe Ceremonies,] ſee the Article: and this is aſſerted by that great Advocate of this Church cited above, and more confidently by a Late Biſhop. Upon this Principle and bottom are all our Ceremonies, and all thoſe at <hi>Rome</hi> founded, and is moſt certainly falſe; as is proved elſewhere.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are held forth in practiſe, as <hi>Moral means</hi> to excite Devotion, and teach and provoke to Duty: the <hi>Surplice</hi> to Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Croſs</hi> to Conſtancy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And upon theſe Reaſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and commanded by the Church her ſelf, <hi>(Preface to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy:)</hi> and by her Champions propugnated, which renders them ſuperſtitious; as will further appear on another Head.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The laſt Rule is [When we have ſome unqueſtionable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſuſpect the deſign of our Governours, to betray the Church to Superſtition and Idolatry, contrary to the known Doctrine of it] enough, and enough! This Symptome hath been viſible for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in ſome chief Rulers of the Church, who were known to be Popiſhly affected: and laboured to bring in Superſtition and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry into the Church, by ſetting up <hi>Images, Crucifixes, Altars</hi> in the Churches, requiring Bowings at the Name of Jeſus, and to, or towards the Altars: Aſſerting holineſs of Times, Places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which God never conſecrated: What ſome in chiefeſt places of the Church are now deſigning, time will manifeſt. Sufficient hath been ſpoken to prove our Ceremonies to be ſuperſtitious, and therefore not to be Impoſed, or if Impoſed, to be repealed, and reverſed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. [Nothing doubtful, or ſuſpected juſtly to be ſinful may be Impoſed in Worſhip.] This was the 6th. <hi>Poſtulatum,</hi> either to be granted, or proved: How far the Rev. <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> hath yielded to this Propoſition, may be ſeen above, and what was evinced from his Conceſſion. Other Learned and Judicious Divines aſſert, and prove it more fully; Take ſome of their own words. Firſt, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Mr. <hi>Hales.</hi> who propounds this as a remedy of Schiſm. [To have all Liturgies and Publick Forms of Service ſo framed, as that they admit not of particular and private Fancies, but contain only ſuch things in which all Chriſtians do agree. To charge the Church with things unneceſſary, was the firſt beginning of all Superſtition and Schiſme: — and concludes, whereſoever faiſe or ſuſpected
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48221:14"/>Opinions are made a part of Church-Liturgy, he that ſeparates is not the Schiſmatick; for it is alike unlawful, to make profeſſion of known, or ſuſpected falſhood, as to put in practiſe unlawful or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected actions.] See more in his Book of Schiſm. Or as his words are cited more largely by Mr. <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> who agrees with him in the Aſſertion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iren.</hi> part. 1. pag. 120, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and gives a ſtrong Reaſon againſt the Impoſition of ſuſpected things. [As for publick Forms of Divine Service ſuch of all things certainly, ſhould be ſo compoſed, as to be the leaſt ſubject to any ſcruples from any perſon whatſoever, being on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe compoſed for the declaration of mens Unity and Conſent in their publick Worſhip.] And let me add my Mite to the Heap;
<note place="margin">See Rom 15.5, 6. &amp; 1 Cor. 1.10.</note> In worſhip there is req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ired <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity</hi> of hearts, rather then <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> in Ceremonies; ſo the Apoſtle: <hi>Be ye all of one mind. Speak the ſame thing, Phil.</hi> 2.2. And all ſhould ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the ſame Prayers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. Which cannot be done in things to any doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or ſuſpected to be falſe or unlawful.</p>
               <p>And now I ſhall not need to prove the Aſſumption. I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> his words cited above, ſpoken indeed of <hi>Image</hi> worſhip, appliable to our Ceremonies. [They are acknowledged by all to be unneceſſary, by many held unlawful, by moſt ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or doubtful;] and therefore may not lawfully be impoſed in Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Laſtly, [No ſignificant thing (or Ceremony) ſignifying ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Favour of God, or the Grace of the Sacrament, or to be a means of receiving any Bleſſing from God, may by men be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in Worſhip: But ſuch are our Ceremonies; <hi>ergo,</hi> &amp;c.] The <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition is fully granted above in the 7th. Conceſſion; and further confirmed thus; Becauſe ſignifications of ſuch things, put upon things or Ceremonies in worſhip make them Sacraments, too like to thoſe of Chriſts Inſtitution, at leaſt (as he) Semi-Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which <hi>Papists</hi> call Sacramentals. And indeed they fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Definition of a Sacrament, given in the Church Catechiſm, [A Sacrament is an outward viſible ſign, of an inward and inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Grace,] and therefore an outward viſible ſign of an inward ſpiritual Grace, is a Sacrament. Now,
<note place="margin">Exod 30.33.</note> as in the <hi>Holy Perfume</hi> in the Old Law, there was a ſtrict Prohibition that no man ſhould dare to make the like, ſo is there a ſtricter prohibition (if ſtricter may be) in the ſecond Commandment, that no man preſume to make a Sacrament, (which is a part of worſhip) or any thing like
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48221:15"/>a Sacrament, or part of worſhip. The Jealouſie of God will not endure it. It was <hi>Jeroboams</hi> ſin (and therefore not ſuch policy as he fancied) to make <hi>a Feaſt, like unto the Feaſt in Judah,</hi> 1 Kings 2.32. It remaines then to prove the <hi>Minor;</hi> that ſuch ſignifications are put upon our Ceremonies; that in their Impoſition ſome of thoſe ſignifications are put upon them, and ſo practiſed by many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That voluntary Services (ſuch as our Ceremonies) are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſignifie and procure the Favour of God in ſome reſpect, was openly profeſſed by a Learned <hi>Rabbi</hi> of this Church, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>cum Licentiâ Superiorum,</hi> as was inſtanced above. And by thoſe that eſteem the Sacrament of Baptiſm, imperfect, without the Croſs; or the other Sacrament irreverently received without Kneeling, it muſt be intended, that thoſe Ceremonies do procure (and therefore ſignifie) the Favour of God: but I let that paſs as the ſenſe of private perſons, (for ſo it will be anſwered) and not as the Judgment of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. [They are Impoſed to ſignifie the Grace of the Sacraments, at leaſt in part,] with this only difference, that the Sacraments do ſignifie the whole Covenant of Grace, or the whole Grace of the Covenant; theſe ſome particular Graces thereof: as the <hi>Surplice</hi> to ſignifie <hi>Purity,</hi> the <hi>Croſs Conſtancy:</hi> and what are theſe but <hi>Semi Sacraments</hi> (as he cals them) and the Definition of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fits them handſomly. The outward ſign of the Surplice ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the inward inviſible Grace of Purity. The outward viſible ſign of the Croſs ſignifies the inward inviſible Grace of Conſtancy in our Profeſſion: ſignified before by Baptiſm; Sacraments are ſigns to remember us of the whole Covenant of Grace, in both the parts; of Grace from God to us; of Duty from us to God. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are impoſed, to ſignifie (they ſay) our Duty to God, but not the Grace of God to us. <hi>Ex. gr.</hi> the Surplice (being pure <hi>white</hi> Linnen) ſignifies what purity, holineſs chaſtity, ſhould be in a Miniſter, (ſay the ſame proportionably of the Croſs.) But does it not alſo ſignifie Grace from God, to work thoſe duties or graces in us? (for they are both graces and duties) If ſo: What differs it from a Sacrament? If not; it will prove an idle and vain Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony; and for that reaſon not to be Impoſed in worſhip, or if Impoſed, to be repealed. In the Old Teſtament, they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, to make, and weare <hi>Fringes, Frontlets, Phylacteries,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48221:15"/>[To look upon it, and to remember all the Commandments of the Lord, and do them, and be holy unto their God,</hi> Numb. 15.39, 40.] And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things appointed by God, no doubt but to the right uſers of them, they were accompanied with grace to perform thoſe duties; and thoſe were part of their Ceremonial Worſhip. But if they had deviſed their Ceremonies of their own heads to the ſame religious ends in vain might they have expected the like efficacy: though ſtill they had been <hi>religious Ceremonies,</hi> and parts of worſhip, but falſe. And when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did add to theſe Ceremonies [by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>broad the Phylacteries, and enlarging the Borders,</hi> (that is, the Fringes) <hi>of their Garments</hi> Mat. 23.5] Our Saviour reproves not only their <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> in ſeeming holier to men; but alſo their <hi>Superſtition,</hi> in ſeeming wiſer then God, in their own additions. As in another caſe of their own Traditions, their <hi>Ablutions</hi> before they did eat, waſhing of Pots, Cups, and Beds, as well as hands, they made this a Ceremony, to ſignifie what <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>holineſs</hi> ought to be in themſelves and others; expecting no doubt the ſame (if not greater) efficacy from this Ceremony as from thoſe Ablutions commanded by God in their Law; and for this our Saviour char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them with <hi>Will-Worſhip,</hi> [Mat. 15.8.9. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the Commandments of men.</hi>] How appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable all this is to our Ceremonies, I need not ſay: the <hi>Surplice</hi> anſwers to their Fringes, the <hi>Croſs</hi> to their Frontlets, being appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Childs Forehead: If any ſhall ſay theſe our Ceremonies as they are only <hi>monitory</hi> of Duty, not <hi>exhibitory</hi> of Grace; ſo the like efficacy is not given to them, by the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our Church. To that ſee the next.</p>
               <p n="3">3. [They are inſtituted (as I conceive by their words) to be a means of receiving ſome Bleſſing from God] that is, to be <hi>moral</hi> cauſes to work thoſe Duties, or Graces in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſers</hi> of <hi>them;</hi> and ſuch (and not <hi>Phyſical</hi> cauſes) were not only thoſe Frontlets, Fringes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the Word and Sacraments alſo of God appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. To make good this Charge, I ſhall produce the words of a Late Advocate of our Ceremonies. [If men put any force or effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy in Circumſtances deviſed by men, which neither God hath promiſed to make good, nor Nature it ſelf is apt to produce, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Form is impreſſed on them by an erroneou Intention.] That more vertue or efficacy is put upon our Ceremonies, then God hath promiſed, or Nature can produce, ſhall be made out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48221:16"/>from their own acknowledgments. 1. The Church it ſelf, in retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and inſtituting them hath theſe words;
<note place="margin">Pref. to the old Liturgy.</note> [We have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with only thoſe Ceremonies, which make to decent Order, and pious Diſcipline, and which <hi>[Note that]</hi> by ſome excellent and ſpecial ſignification, are able to call to memory, a Duty to be performed to God, in the ſtupid mind of man to his edification] It muſt be remembred here: 1. That theſe Ceremonies are to be uſed in the Worſhip of God. 2. They are able to mind men of a Duty to God. 3. They are uſeful not to civil, but ſpiritual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification: juſt as the Frontlets and other Ceremonies were. Now this is a ſupernatural effect expected by the uſe of them, which neither by any promiſe of God, nor by their own nature, they are able to produce. But 2. the <hi>Apologiſts,</hi> who underſtood the mind of the Church, and were approved by her. Go further: As,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. Pol.</note> 1. The Learned <hi>Hooker</hi> affirms, [That Ceremonies do leave a ſtronger and deeper Impreſſion.] He muſt mean it, as I ſuppoſe, of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Impreſſion, (being uſed in the Worſhip of God) and that ſtronger and deeper then the very Ordinances of God do exhibite, or elſe they are idle, and needleſs, where the ſame or an equal Impreſſion, is made by the Ordinances themſelves; <hi>ex. gr.</hi> The <hi>Croſs</hi> uſed in Baptiſm, muſt be ſuppoſed to make a deeper Impreſſion then Baptiſm it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which if it be not Superſtition in a high degree, I know not what is. 2. The Learned Dr. <hi>Field</hi> ſpeaks fuller to the purpoſe: Who having ſtrongly confuted the Popiſh Superſtitions, becauſe they put a ſupernatural force in theſe Ceremonies: addes this; <q>[Our Ceremonies are adhibited, to put in mind,
<note place="margin">Of the Chur. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 30. <hi>ad ſinem.</hi>
                     </note> and (mark this) to excite greater Fervour and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to be of force to expreſs ſuch ſpiritual and heavenly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, diſpoſitions, motions, or deſires, ſuch a are or ought to be in men.]</q> And I pray, what did the Legal Ceremonies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God (before-mentioned) do more? Or what is this leſs then is intended to be effected by <hi>Romiſh</hi> Ceremonies? If it be ſaid (as it is) [Our Ceremonies are monitory only,
<note place="margin">D. B.</note> external oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and objects, whereby the mind of man worketh upon its ſelf, not cauſes working by ſome vertue in them.] I Anſwer, 1. The very Ordinances of God. Word and Sacraments, and thoſe other named Ceremonies, did not work <hi>phyſically</hi> by any vertue in them, but morally by the Inſtitution of God; and yet were they and are means to procure and receive a Bleſſing from God. 2. The
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48221:16"/>words are plain, they are appointed to excite ſpiritual Devotion, make ſtronger impreſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is not that a working cauſe, or a <hi>means</hi> uſed in worſhip to thoſe ends? which is flatly againſt the Second Commandment. 3. If they ſtir up ſpiritual devotion, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly affections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not thoſe ſupernatural effects? 4. If they excite ſuch effects in mens hearts, muſt not that preſuppoſe, all that uſe them to be ſpiritually minded, and diſpoſed? How elſe can they ſtir up in them, thoſe affections that are not in them? But then what uſe are they of to Natural and carnal men? There is a carnal Devotion, as well as ſpiritual. To ſtir up carnal devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not make them acceptable to God: If they ſtir up ſpiritual devotion in carnal men, is not that a ſupernatural effect aſcribed to humane Ceremonies? And are they not made hereby as <hi>operative,</hi> and exhibitive of Grace as thoſe Inſtituted by God? Let it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered! I could enlarge this Diſcourſe with other Teſtimonies of Learned Ceremonialiſts; to the ſame purpoſe: and with the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and Opinion of many that dote upon them, who expect <hi>Grace Favour,</hi> and a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> from God, upon ſuch Devotion: But I forbear, and now draw up the Argument into one view againſt the Impoſition of our Ceremonies, <hi>twiſted</hi> up of a ſix-fold Cord, which will not eaſily be broken. Thus, [Nothing ſinful, inexpedient, purely-indifferent, ſuperſtitious, doubtful, or ſignificant Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may by men be Impoſed in Divine Worſhip] But our Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are guilty of all theſe Crimes; therefore they may not by men be Impoſed in Worſhip, and conſequently if Impoſed, to be repealed, which was our firſt undertaking, now performed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>II. <hi>Of Submiſſion to them, if Impoſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The hardeſt and greateſt work is now over, and I ſhall not need to be long or large in the two following Particulars As to the preſent Queſtion. [Whether if ſuch things be Impoſed by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we may lawfully ſubmit unto them?] It is often pretended by the <hi>Caſuist</hi> and others, [that though the things be Inconvenient, and Inexpedient, yet the Command of Authority alters the ſtate of the Queſt. <hi>pag.</hi> 39, 69, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and makes them to us neceſſary by a neceſſity of Obedience, (though not ſo in their own natures) by vertue of a Divine Commandment. <hi>[Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves.]</hi> Indeed this pretence ſeems to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48221:17"/>put a demur to the Caſe: and is the foundation of all his Diſcourſe in the greateſt part of it, concerning ſubmiſſion to ſuch Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But it is eaſily removed, by a Diſtinction or two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the ſenſe of the word <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> which he ſubſtitutes for the word <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> to mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lifie the harſhneſs thereof, as was noted in the Explication of Termes, which having once preſumed to do, he then ſuppoſes (unjuſtly alſo) thoſe things now called <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> to be things lawful not only in their own nature, and <hi>extracultum,</hi> but alſo in their uſe, and in Worſhip, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by himſelf, when he makes things inconvenient in their uſe to be ſinful, <hi>p.</hi> 68. Of which afore.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of things inexpedient or inconvenient, which may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be of two ſorts. 1. In regard of meer Circumſtances of Worſhip, as an inconvenient place, or an unſeaſonable time there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which muſt be taken, or no other allowed for publick worſhip, wherein the Authority may ſin in Impoſing: as violating, the Rules of Decency, Order, or Edification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. but the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſins not in ſubmitting, yea ſhould ſin in not ſubmitting. 2. With reſpect to <hi>humane Ceremonies,</hi> which are inconvenient, and inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in their uſe, that is hurtful to the Worſhip, or Worſhippers: which are alwaies ſinful in worſhip, and may no more lawfully be ſubmitted to, then Impoſed in worſhip, as he hath often granted. Now then our Ceremonies being proved to be ſo many waies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient, that is, ſinful in worſhip, one Argument (but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated one, and ſo much the ſtronger) will diſpatch the buſineſs. Thus. [No ſinful, inexpedient, unneceſſary, ſuperſtitious, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſignificant Ceremonies, may be ſubmitted to, if Impoſed in Worſhip. But our Ceremonies are proved to be ſuch; <hi>ergo</hi> they may not be ſubmitted to.] Againſt this Concluſion neither the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church, nor pretended <hi>Duty,</hi> nor too much deſired <hi>Safety</hi> (his threefold Cord, uſed to draw others to Conformity with himſelf) can diſpenſe, till this Argument be enervated, and made voyd. I proceed to the laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>III. <hi>Of Aſſenting and Conſenting to them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This third and laſt Queſtion is newly occaſioned by the Late Act for Uniformity, and the too general compliance of Miniſters, with it: not only to ſubmit to the Ceremenies, and other things
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48221:17"/>Impoſed as to Practiſe, (which in ſome things might be tollerable) but alſo to enſlave their Judgments, to a full approbation of all and every thing contained in, and preſcribed by it. Which one would think, ſhould have ſtumbled many more till they had ſerio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered both what the things are (which are very many) and alſo have ſufficient ground for ſo large a Submiſſion. When it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that many of the Declarers and Subſcribers, never ſaw the Book, nor conſidered the Reaſons of ſo deep an Engagement, but haſtily ſwallowed down all, with an Implicite Faith truſting to their Rulers. Now if there be but one thing Inexpedient in it, one thing falſe, or evil, that is ſinful: As ſubmiſſion to ſo univerſal a Practiſe of it, is proved unlawful, ſo the giving an [unfeigned aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and conſent to all and every thing contained in it] can by no good Conſcience be juſtified. That Act takes in the whole Book, as now it is Publiſhed and Eſtabliſhed. And containes the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, or rather Volume of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Proteſtant, Epiſcopal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Form of Doctrine, or Confeſſion of Faith in the 39, Articles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Mode of Worſhip in the Liturgy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Model of Diſcipline in the Book of Ordination or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons.] All theſe to be at one Lump, ſubmitted, ſubſcribed, aſſented, conſented to, and that unfeignedly; It was partly yielded above, that in ſome caſes it may be lawful not only for peace ſake, but alſo for Conſcience ſake, to ſubmit to ſome thing Inconvenient, (as an Inconvenient Circumſtance) if Impoſed by a lawful Authority: But now the Queſtion is, of declaring openly an unfeigned aſſent and conſent to a thing (any thing, if any there be) Inconvenient in the Book, which to me imports an Approbation of it: as ſhall be ſhewed ere long: I ſhall only deſire to remember the Explication of the Terms. That <hi>Aſſent hath respect to the truth of a thing: Conſent to the Goodneſs: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned to the ſincerity of both.</hi> I now propound the Queſtion the third time.</p>
               <q>Whether it be lawful for Miniſters to conform ſo far to the Late eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Book for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, as Publickly to declare an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent, to all and every thing contained in, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by it?</q>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:48221:18"/>
               <p>To the Deciſion of this great Queſtion, one would eaſily think, little need be ſaid, conſidering what hath been ſaid already, againſt divers things contained in that Book; any one whereof if proved ſinful (as I believe ſome are, and more will be) might be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent bar to ſuſpend either Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt or Conſent to the truth or good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, much more the practiſe of them, which yet is promiſed in the Subſcription to them; I ſhall argue firſt <hi>ex conceſſis &amp; probatis;</hi> and then add ſome more ſpecial Reaſons in ſome Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In General; thus I aſſault them. [If divers things Impoſed and to be ſubmitted to be ſinful, (the Impoſition and Submiſſion to them being therefore ſinful) then it is much more ſinful to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to them, yea to all and every thing contained in and preſcribed by that Book; but the Antecedent is moſt true, and aſſerted by themſelves, and where they are ſhut, proved ſo to be: the Conſequence is made undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Apoſtles Logick and Divinity, [<hi>Rom</hi> 1 <hi>ult</hi> Who though they know that <hi>they that do ſuch things are guilty or worthy of death;</hi> not only do ſuch things, but alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, conſent to, or favour them that do them.] The Argument is taken <hi>a minore ad majus:</hi> It is bad to do things ſinful, eſpecially againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Conſcience, but much worſe to aſſent and conſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly to the truth, and goodneſs of ſuch things. The reaſon is, becauſe a man may do a thing ſinful, either out of Ignorance, or inadvertency, or the violence of a Temptation; but he cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly aſſent, and conſent to the doing of them, or to them that do them, without deliberation, and knowingly againſt his clearly convinced Conſcience. And the more of <hi>Will</hi> is in a ſin, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the aggravation of it. Now this is obſervable, that few Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Miniſters there are, which do not believe ſome things in that Book to be inconvenient, burdenſom, troubleſom, and ſcarce Orthodox, either in Doctrine, Worſhip, or Diſcipline: And ſome in my hearing have already complained, that the burden to read all preſcribed, and to preach when they have done, (as they ought to do, being of Divine Inſtitution) is a Burden which they are not able to bear, as ſome of their Forefathers complained. And to omit or ſhorten Preaching, to enlarge the Church-Service, they are ready to profeſs to be againſt their Conſciences; as a making voyd the Commandment of God, by obſerving the Traditions of men.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48221:18"/>2. [It is highly ſinful to Aſſent and Conſent unfeignedly to things Inexpedient, purely Indifferent, (that is Idle, or Uſeleſs) Superſtitious, Doubtful, or Significant Humane Ceremonies, as againſt the Second and Third Commandments,] and becauſe ſuch things are ſinful in Worſhip. But to ſome ſuch things, yea many, do they <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent,</hi> who declare their aſſent and conſent to all and every thing Contained in, and Preſcribed by that Book, as hath clearly been proved, <hi>ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. [It is highly Preſumptuous, Sacrilegious, if not Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, to make that Book equal to the <hi>Sacred Bible,</hi> and the Powers Impoſing it, as infallible, as thoſe were that wrote the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, (as the <hi>Pope</hi> does the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and the Traditions of the Church.)] But this is done by all that in that manner make that Declaration: For what can more be declared and aſſerted of the Holy <hi>Canonical,</hi> Spirit inſpired Scriptures, then an unfeigned aſſent to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and conſent to the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of all and every thing contained in thoſe Books?</p>
               <p n="4">4. [To aſſent and conſent to the Impoſition of things unlawful, in Worſhip, is to make themſelves twice guilty of ſin, once as they aſſent and conſent to things unlawful, and a ſecond time, as they confirm the Impoſers in that ſinful Impoſition. For when will they repent of, or repeal theſe ſinful Impoſitions, when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to be true, and lawful, by ſo many complying Miniſters in ſo high a Declaration?</p>
               <p n="5">5. To declare and profeſs ſo publickly before God and their People, their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing in that Book: believing, that ſome things are Inconvenient and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient, which they wiſh were removed, is groſs Diſſimulation, and deſperate hypocriſie. But many of the Complyers do believe and confeſs ſome ſuch things to be contained in that Book, either not true, or not lawful, and yet aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained in it. Or ſuppoſe them ſo corrupted in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Judgments, as to be perſwaded of the Goodneſs and Truth of all and every thing therein, it may eaſily be proved, and hath been already, that ſome things in it are not true, as to matter of Doctrine, and ſome things not lawful, as to matter of Worſhip or Diſcipline, if I might ſafely diſpute againſt that Book, having a Law to render it liable to a <hi>Premunire.</hi> But Truth is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48221:19"/>Truth, and to be acknowledged, when we are called to give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to it. This hath been done by many, and not yet anſwered. The Book containes the whole of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, and in every one of thoſe Defects, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and Corruptions manifeſted; and yet without Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of many things, impoſed and preſſed on us with more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour then formerly. See ſome Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Doctrine. As 1. In the Articles of Religion, <hi>Art.</hi> 20. [The Church hath power to decree Rites and Ceremonies,] which words being ambiguous, taken either for meer Circumſtances of Worſhip, for Order, Decency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or for Sacred Rites, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ceremonies; In the firſt ſenſe they are true, but doubtful: To which no unfeigned aſſent can be given, till the diſtinction be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: In the laſt ſenſe (in which they are uſually taken,) they are proved to be falſe, above in this Diſcourſe. And ſome other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal points of Doctrine there are ſo doubtfully worded, that as <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> have gloſſed them to their Opinions, ſo no tender Conſcience can ſafely give ſo full aſſent to them as true, till they be explained, which was formerly denied and prohibited to be made by thoſe that ſubſcribed them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> ſome <hi>Doctrinals</hi> are delivered and preſcribed to be aſſented to; as firſt, a falſe Tranſlation of the Pſalmes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the errours of the Vulgar <hi>Latine,</hi> ſtill retained to be read; not to ſpeak of their leaving out of the Titles of many Pſalmes, which in <hi>Hebrew</hi> are Canonical Scripture. And it is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to take from the word of God as to add to it; unleſs they intend to make amends for their Subſtraction of ſome, by Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of other things: and that is ſufficiently done, by addition of ſome <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Pſalmes, <hi>Te Deum, Benedicite,</hi> and a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chapters of the Bookes called <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> to be read, a moſt for two moneths together; ſome whereof are falſe, and as very lying Legends as thoſe uſed in the Romiſh Churches, and ſome newly added not in before, as the Hiſtory of <hi>Suſanna, Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</hi> And what is this but (as they at <hi>Rome</hi>) a Canonizing in part, of the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> making it equal to the Scripture in Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as part of their Doctrine; I might add that Aſſertion [That all Children Baptized are really regenerated, and want nothing neceſſary to their Salvation] which drawes after it, all or moſt of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48221:19"/>the <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Tenents</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Homilies</hi> are part of the Doctrine of the Church, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the 35 Canon, and preſcribed to be read by every Miniſter, and now with the Articles enjoyned to be aſſented to unfeignedly as true. In theſe have been obſerved ſome falſe Doctrines; as to juſtifie <hi>plurality</hi> of Wives, by the old Fathers, <hi>Hom. Of the time and place of Prayer,</hi> pag. 147. That Almes purgeth away all ſins, delivereth from death, <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. <hi>Of Almes,</hi> pag. 16. For proof whereof is cited, as good Scripture, <hi>Tobit</hi> 4.10. &amp; the Son of <hi>Syrach.</hi> Dare any Orthodox Miniſter declare his unfeigned aſſent to the Truth of theſe Doctrines? yet this is done by too many.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In <hi>Worſhip.</hi> There are ſome things not good, that is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to which yet an unfeigned conſent is to be given. For the Ceremonies they are largely diſcovered to be ſinful and unlawful above. To which may be added the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Pſalmes and Books made not only equal with the Divine Scriptures, but alſo parts of Divine Service, as fully as any part of the Word of God. Add to theſe the <hi>Reſponds</hi> of the Clerk and People, Women, Boyes and Wenches, clearly againſt the Apoſtles Rules of Decency, Order, Edification, as may be eaſily manifeſted. And more might be ſaid concerning the Miniſters change of places, poſtures, ridiculous geſticulations, as if Divine Service were ſome Play or Comedy to be acted; which cauſes the Name of God to be taken in vain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the third Commandment: Can any pious devout Miniſter give his unfaigned conſent to theſe as good?</p>
               <p n="3">3. In <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> The Book of Ordination is the <hi>Epitome</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, now joyned and eſtabliſhed with the Articles and Liturgy. But there are ſome things in them proved to be falſe. As 1. That there are three kinds or Orders of Church Officers; <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> when Scripture knowes but two: It being proved and confeſſed by Epiſcopal men, that in Scripture a Biſhop and a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter are one and the ſame Order and Office. 2. That <hi>Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by Presbyters is null. I add no more: To all theſe either falſe or unlawful do they aſſent and conſent, which how they can do with a good Conſcience, I underſtand not, but do admire.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And Laſtly, (beſides the burdens they have laid upon their weak Brethren, in a very conſiderable number, and the hurt they have done to the Church in the loſs of ſo many Able Miniſters, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48221:20"/>the gratifying of Antichriſt) they have by their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained in and preſcribed by that Book, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, as precluded all future hopes of Reformation, ſo alſo enſlaved themſelves, and their Succeſſors of the Clergy to the power and yoke of Epiſcopal Tyranny: Juſt in the ſame manner, (if not meaſure) as the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Clergy are enſlaved to the Pope, without all hope of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, till either Antichriſt be fallen, or thoſe ſtrict Lawes for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity be repealed and broken: This is one chief Character of Antichriſt, that he cauſeth all his Subject; (eſpecially the Clergy) <hi>to receive a Mark in their right hand, and in their Forehead, that none may buy or ſell that want this Mark.</hi> How far this is appliable to our preſent condition, any wiſe man will eaſily diſcern. The Biſhops have now obtained their long Deſire, and Deſign, to <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due,</hi> and enſlave the Clergy to themſelves (and with them the People) they having boared their Eares to their Door poſts, and received a mark in their Foreheads, by their ſo Publick <hi>Declaration,</hi> and in their <hi>Right Hand</hi> by their <hi>Subſcription,</hi> without which no Miniſter may buy or ſell, that is, deal in any thing that concernes his Miniſterial Office, or as a Schollar, to get a Livelihood. And whether this be not the ſlaying of the Witneſſes (Natural or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil) ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> or the Forerunner of it, I leave to prudent men to determine. And here I reſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:48221:20"/>
            <head>The Grand Caſe conſidered, as to the double Supplement an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed thereunto.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>I. <hi>Touching Things Inexpedient.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Begin with this (though it ſtand laſt in the Grand Caſe) partly becauſe it is intended to be a <hi>Support</hi> to uphold his former Tract, which I have throughly ventilated; and partly becauſe it muſt be the Foundation of the Main Caſe of <hi>Conformity</hi> to the Declarations required in the Late Act. For if the things in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, be not only <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> or burdenſom, but alſo <hi>Inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> that is, (according to his own Expoſition of the word) <hi>Sinful, [In vain is the Net ſpread before the eyes of any Fowl.]</hi> No man of any good Conſcience, can, or dare be taken with ſuch <hi>Chaffe,</hi> as he hath here ſcattered, in ſtead of good Corn, to beguile and miſlead his Readers.</p>
               <p>Before I conſider, what <hi>freſh Supply</hi> he hath brought, I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſome few Obſervations, as grounds to ſhake and fruſtrate all this ſecond Undertaking.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He here again (as was complained of, and manifeſted, on his former caſes) confounds <hi>Inexpedient</hi> with <hi>Inconvenient.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we hear of <q>[Things ſimply inexpedient, <hi>p.</hi> 144. which he expounds by things Inconvenient, <hi>p.</hi> 147. No ſmall Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>p.</hi> 150. For ſome Inconveniences impoſed on us, we ought not to quit our Miniſtry.]</q> (Which we profeſs we would not do) and other the like Paſſages: when yet he told us, <q>[Things not Expedient in Worſhip ought not to be Impoſed, or if Impoſed, to be Submitted to.]</q> as anon we ſhall hear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Inexpedient</hi> may be taken, either <hi>negatively,</hi> for a thing not Expedient; or <hi>poſitively,</hi> for ſomething hurtful: For as, <hi>Expedient</hi> is taken for <hi>uſeful, helpful,</hi> to the buſineſs we are about: So a thing <hi>Inexpedient</hi> (in a flat oppoſition, as was ſaid) may be taken either way, for not-uſeful, or hurtful to it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48221:21"/>3. A thing inexpediently <hi>evil,</hi> or hurtful in Worſhip, may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken either for <hi>malum poenae,</hi> as troubleſom, or burdenſom, or for <hi>malum culpae,</hi> a thing ſinful. The <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt</hi> does not clearly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh theſe two ſenſes, and which he meanes; and therefore ſeemes ſecretly to paſs <hi>a genere in genus:</hi> from one kind to another.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A thing may be <hi>ſinful,</hi> either in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> or in <hi>its uſe</hi> in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, from ſome Circumſtance of time or place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is given us by the <hi>Caſuiſt, p.</hi> 68. of the former <hi>Tract,</hi> and we ſhall make uſe of it hereafter.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A thing may be <hi>Inexpedient</hi> in two Reſpects; 1. In matters of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and common <hi>Affairs,</hi> or in matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and Worſhip. Some Aſſertions of his, are true and allowable in the firſt, but not in the ſecond reſpect. I needed not to have noted this, but that he ſeems to have forgotten (what he firſt intended) that he is tied to ſpeak to things <hi>Inexpedient</hi> in Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Things <hi>evil</hi> and Inexpedient, in both ſenſes, as penally or ſinfully ſuch, may be conſidered or compared 3 waies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. One evil of puniſhment with another, a leſſer with a greater; and here the Rule is, <hi>e malis minimum;</hi> chuſe the leaſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An evil of puniſhment, with an evil of ſin; and here the Rule is, The greateſt evil of puniſhment muſt be choſen, rather then the leaſt evil of ſin, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25.</p>
               <p n="3">3. One evil of ſin with another, leſſer, equal, or greater; and here the Rule is, <hi>e malis neatrum, vel nullum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now we come to the Caſe propounded <q>[Whether, or how far things inexpedient</q> (not impoſed in Worſhip, for that is peremptorily denied by the <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt</hi> in the former Tract, but) may be ſubmitted to, if impoſed, by Authority?] That was the Caſe before. <q>[What is to be done, when things Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient are impoſed?</q> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> in Worſhip: Now an <hi>Objection,</hi> it ſeemes, is lately flarted, and an Argument enforced from his own Principles, for the Negative, in this manner:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Nothing ſinful in Worſhip may be ſubmitted to, though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Authority; which is now proved by Scripture, we may not do evil, that good may come thereby: But Inexpedient things impoſed in Worſhip are ſinful; <hi>ergo</hi> not to be ſubmitted to.]</q> The <hi>Major</hi> as it is obvious to any Religious Conſcience, ſo it is often aſſerted in the other Tract: The <hi>Minor</hi> is alſo granted in the very terms: <q>[All Indifferent things not expedient, are not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48221:21"/>lawful, but finful, <hi>p.</hi> 36.] And <hi>p.</hi> 34. Things not expedient to be done, ought not to be done.]</q> What ſaies he now to it? Both the Propoſitions being his own, he muſt either yield the Cauſe, and own the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> or diſtinguiſh of one, or both the Propoſitions; which latter he attempts to do, as followeth:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[Things are evil or unlawful, either <hi>in specie,</hi> or <hi>in genere</hi> only, either in themſelves, as prohibited by ſome ſpecial Law, Natural or Poſitive; or in reſpect to ſome Circumſtance or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.]</q> To which I reply in this manner; deſiring to know to which Propoſition he will apply this Diſtinction. 1. If to the <hi>Major,</hi> it muſt be thus; <q>[Things ſinful againſt a ſpecial Commandment, may not be ſubmitted to in Worſhip, but things forbidden by a general Commandment, may, if impoſed by Authority.]</q> For ſo he ſaies: <q>[Things of the ſecond kind, prohibited in general, are not a violation of a ſpecial Law of God, but of a general, <hi>p.</hi> 145.]</q> And ſuch may be lawfully ſubmitted to, or I know not what to make of his words: To ſay, that things prohibited by a <hi>general</hi> Law, are not a violation of a ſpecial Law, is a vulgar truth, and not beſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>R. Caſuiſts</hi> Learning. And to ſay, things evil and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful either by a ſpecial or general Law, are not ſinful, will leſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeem his Wiſdom; for that is a contradiction: Things ſinful (ſuch are all prohibited by any Law of God) are not ſinful. 2. If he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his Diſtinction to the <hi>Minor,</hi> it muſt, I ſuppoſe be thus: <q>[Things Inexpedient are of two ſorrs; either ſuch as are prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by a ſpecial, or by a general Comandment: the firſt ſort are ſinful, and not to be ſubmitted to, but the latter may.]</q> Will he ſtand to this? May any ſinful thing in Worſhip be ſubmitted to? Hath he not aſſerted the contrary, in the caſe of ſinful things impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Beſides, this Diſtinction comes here too late, being neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to have been uſed, before he gave us that univerſal Propoſition: <q>[All Indifferent things not-expedient, are not lawful, but ſinful.]</q> And now, belike, ſome <hi>not-expedient</hi> things are not ſinful, but law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Worſhip. 3. Or if he ſhall ſay, by <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> he meanes only things <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> burdenſom perhaps, but not ſinful: the firſt may be ſubmitted to, not the ſecond: He ſaies true, but then he <hi>equivocates</hi> with us, in both his Tracts, in the ſenſe of the word, Inexpedient: having told us, that all Inexpedient things in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, were ſinful, and not to be done: and ſo ſlips <hi>a genere in gemes.</hi> 4. He told us alſo, ſome things were ſinful in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48221:22"/>by <hi>Inconveniency</hi> in their uſe, <hi>p.</hi> 68. But both are ſinful, and can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them be lawfully ſubmitted to? 5. His Inſtances of things prohibited <hi>in genere,</hi> are <hi>Indecencies,</hi> and Diſorders, and the like, in Worſhip. But this is a great Miſtake, in a <hi>Divine,</hi> in a <hi>Caſuiſt:</hi> For there are as ſpecial Lawes againſt them, either in Nature, or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and as Moral, as againſt Murder, or Theft; <hi>viz.</hi> either the Second or Third Commandments, as Additions to the Worſhip, or prophanation of it, and conſequently a <hi>taking of Gods Name in vain;</hi> or by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. where ſpecially forbidden: Yea, they ſeem prohibited by a Law of Nature, <q>[A ſtanding Law, (ſaid he) never to be croſſed by any Authority under Heaven, yea the God of Heaven being the God of Order, will never reverſe it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 43. of the other Caſes: If not impoſed, nor may they be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to: The Reaſon is the ſame for both, becauſe they are ſinful <hi>in their uſe,</hi> or by the circumſtance of the time, when uſed in Worſhip, being now <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> and for that reaſon both unlawful to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or if impoſed, to be ſubmitted to, <hi>p.</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>Hereupon it ſeemes ſtrange to me, which here he ſaies; <q>[If the Inexpediency of ſuch a thing, for which alone it is prohibited, be either ſeparated from it, or overballanced, it becomes repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to no Law at all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> For, 1. This is as if he ſhould ſay, ſeparate the ſin from it, and it is not ſinful: What is the ſin of a thing inexpedient in Worſhip, but the uſe of it in Worſhip? Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the uſe of ſuch a thing from Worſhip, and it may be lawfully u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of Worſhip: <hi>e. g.</hi> a <hi>Surplice,</hi> and the Sign of the <hi>Croſs</hi> uſed in Worſhip, as <hi>Symbolical Rites,</hi> or Ceremonies, we ſay, are ſinful: but out of Worſhip, the one may be lawfully uſed, by a <hi>Groom</hi> or Porter; the other for a <hi>Sign</hi> of a dwelling houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the ſin and the thing uſed, are inſeparable. 2. Neither can the ſinful <hi>Inexpediency</hi> be overballanced by any external, temporal, Expediencies: <q>[An evil of ſin may not be done, to prevent the greateſt poenal evil, or to procure the greateſt temporal good.]</q> And here he ſecretly flides from one kind of evil to another. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins.</hi> Teſtimony is not to the purpoſe; for he ſpeakes of <hi>Civil uſages,</hi> or Cuſtomes of the place, and not of Religious Rites or Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               <p>The like <hi>Miſtakes</hi> are in the next. <q>[That which by reaſon of Circumſtances only, is evil, or unlawful, is ſo accidentally, and may be not immutably ſo.]</q> The firſt part is true; but a thing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48221:22"/>which is accidentally evil, may be immutably ſo, in its uſe, in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as an <hi>Indecency,</hi> or Diſorder in Worſhip, is alwaies evil; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully evil, as was confeſſed. 2. <q>[That which is evil by accident, in one reſpect, may be good, yea better than another.]</q> True alſo, if he ſpeak of things <hi>poenally</hi> evil: But if the thing be <hi>ſinfully</hi> evil, (though but in <hi>the uſe,</hi> in Worſhip) all the reſpects in the world cannot make it good, much leſs, better to be done in Worſhip. 3. Hence the thing that ſeemed, and was <hi>ſinfully</hi> Inexpedient, can by no Circumſtances penally evil, be made (as he ſaies) expedient, much leſs lawful, and neceſſary: for ſo we may, yea muſt do evil, that good may come thereby. <hi>Polanus</hi> his Rule is <hi>Golden,</hi> and good in civil things penally evil; there the greater and more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diencies muſt overballance the leſſer and fewer; but is a <hi>Leaden</hi> Rule, when ſinful and penal evils meet together; the firſt muſt be left undone, whatever becomes of the other.</p>
               <p>We muſt not do evil, to obtain good. He returnes to this. <q>[Yet we muſt do good to prevent evil, though the thing be good for nothing elſe.]</q> I pray what is the meaning of the Apoſtles Rule? <q>[We muſt not do the leaſt ſinful evil, to obtain the greateſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral good:]</q> But he by <hi>evil,</hi> underſtands ſome <hi>poenal evil</hi> (not moral or ſinful) when he ſaies, we muſt do good, to prevent evil: What good? Morally good? That's true, but then he ſecretly begs the Queſtion, that Inexpedient things are morally good, in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; or if otherwiſe, then he allowes us to ſin, to prevent ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal evil: And what means he by evil, which we muſt prevent? If only penal, he permits us to do a ſinful evil to prevent ſome penal evil, or if ſinful, then he allows us to prevent one ſin by doing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For ſuch we take things Inexpedient in worſhip to be. But (by the way) this is but an ill <hi>Character</hi> of the good he intends, <hi>that it is good for nothing elſe</hi> but to prevent the evil of ſuffering: I leave him to apply it. I ſhall not now ſtand to anſwer what he ſaies of the Apoſtles making of ſome inconvenient things <hi>neceſſary:</hi> It will come again more fitly, and fully to be conſidered in the next Caſe. All <hi>I</hi> ſay now, is but this; That if <hi>Expediency</hi> will make a thing good, &amp; neceſſary, and our duty to do (as he aſſerts) then it may ſeem reaſonable, at leaſt, in worſhip, that <hi>Inexpediency</hi> ſhould ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a thing evil, and unlawful, and make it ones Duty not to do it.</p>
               <p>The Teſtimonies of <hi>Cypr. Ambroſe, Auguſt.</hi> are eaſily anſwered,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48221:23"/>in a few words: They ſpeak not of <hi>Myſtical Rites,</hi> or ſignificant Ceremonies, but of ſome civil external <hi>Uſages</hi> gotten into worſhip; different in divers places; as <hi>Socrates</hi> tells us of many, in his time; as in obſervation of <hi>Eaſter</hi> or <hi>Lent:</hi> in receiving the Lords Supper at Evening or Morning, ſtanding or ſitting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such an Uſage in Reformed Churches, is, that ſomewhere the Miniſters preach with heads covered, otherwhere, bare-headed, and many the like: In ſuch things, thoſe <hi>Ancients</hi> adviſe to conform to the Uſages of the places where they come: but ſurely, would never have wiſe people to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in things inexpediently ſinful, in worſhip, in any place.</p>
               <p>The ſame may be ſaid for Forreign and home-reformed Divines. <q>[Do not they (they abroad) either approve our Uſages, or diſlike them only as inconvenient? and thoſe they diſlike as ſuch, do they not yet earneſtly perſwade to conformity to them, from a ſad proſpect of greater Inconveniencies, the diſquiet of the Church, provoking Governours, and the laying aſide the work of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel?]</q>
                  <note place="margin">D. A. <hi>Freſh Suite</hi> part 2. p. 456.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> might anſwer many things, but a Learned and Pious <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> hath done it to my hands at large, to whom <hi>I</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt,</hi> for full ſatisfaction. The ſumme is this:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some of thoſe Learned men, did, at the beginning of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and before they had ſtudied the Controverſie about Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, ſuppoſe our <hi>Uſages</hi> to be only <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> and burdens, and therefore adviſed, that for ſome Inconveniences impoſed here, they ſhould not quit their Miniſtry, or hazard the Church. (Which Counſel we ſhould be willing to embrace, were not many things to us unlawful.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some of them, yea many, upon more ſerious Conſideration, do in their latter Writings, declare their Judgment of them, that they are unlawful.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Being in ſome perplexities, what to anſwer to thoſe Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences feared, and out of tender humane Compaſſion to their Brethren here, like to ſuffer poverty, and hardſhip, did adviſe, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively,</hi> rather to Conformity, than to quit their Miniſtry; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own Judgment. This, and much more, that Learned <hi>Profeſsour.</hi> They did not therefore ſo ſweetly agree together, as is pretended; for they agreed not with themſelves.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Illiricus,</hi> who differed from the reſt of his Brethren, in matter of <hi>Conformity;</hi> it was only or chiefly with reſpect to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim,</hi> impoſed by the <hi>Emperour;</hi> wherein were many <hi>Popiſh Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:48221:23"/>he had better ground to oppoſe that Conformity, than others had to perſwade unto it: And if ſome things now impoſed, be (to us) as unlawful as thoſe were, they that now refuſe, have as good, (if not the ſame) Apology for themſelves. And if that only was his <hi>Crime,</hi> and occaſioned ſo many tumults, he was unjuſtly charged by <hi>Beza,</hi> 
                  <q>[That he promoted Popery, as if he had been hired by the Pope.]</q> unleſs any will ſay, the preaching of the Goſpel by the Apoſtles, was the cauſe of ſo many Tumults, where-ever they came. But rather, they that impoſed thoſe <hi>Errours,</hi> were the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and they that conformed to them, were the <hi>Occaſioners</hi> of thoſe Calamities, which fell upon <hi>Non-conformers:</hi> and did the <hi>Pope</hi> more ſervice, by ſilencing thoſe Pious men, from Preaching againſt thoſe Errours. If <hi>Illiricus</hi> was an <hi>hot-ſpirited</hi> man, and had other Errours of his own (as this for one, that <hi>Sin was a Subſtance,</hi> &amp;c.) which he too vehemently maintained, he might deſerve that black <hi>Character,</hi> given him by the <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> but not for perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> to lay down their Miniſtry, rather than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to thoſe many <hi>Popiſh Errours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for our own <hi>Divines,</hi> at home, that they were <hi>ſubdued</hi> by this Principle <q>[That we ought rather to conform to ſome things Inexpedient, (that is Inconvenient) than to lay down our <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi>]</q> is partly true, of ſome of them, that at firſt, taking things impoſed to be only <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> and not unlawful, they did, in ſome things comply; But it is as evident, that they did eſteem fome things <hi>unlawful,</hi> and (like men under ſad temptations) did contradict themſelves; an example whereof, the <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt</hi> gave us, in one of the moſt eminent among them, in his other Tract, <hi>p.</hi> 101. But the truth is, moſt of thoſe named by him, lived, and died <hi>Nonconformiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Mr. <hi>Sprint,</hi> as he was prevailed upon, to conform, by that ſuppoſed, not proved Principle, that our <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, not unlawful; ſo no marvel, if he upon the ſame Principle, prevailed with others, perhaps unacquainted, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtudied in the Controverſie, and willing to be perſwaded, for ſome reaſons of their own. And if our <hi>Rev. Caſ.</hi> perceive any <hi>bloſſoms,</hi> to appear in ſome, by the influence of his Reſolutions, I fear it is with them, as with ſome over-forward trees, that <hi>bloſſome</hi> in <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> and are blaſted by ſome <hi>March</hi> winds, and Froſts: when they ſhall ſee themſelves deceived, in the Application of that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48221:24"/>and find ſome things preſumed to be only <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> (not proved ſuch by their Author) to appear, and be <hi>unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>2. <hi>Touching the Impoſition of things unlawful.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In the propoſition of this <hi>Caſe,</hi> we muſt rather take his meaning than his words. The Queſtion is not of the <hi>Impoſition,</hi> but of the <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to unlawful things, if they be impoſed. He hath in his former Tract, ſtrongly argued againſt the <hi>Impoſition,</hi> of not only <hi>unlawful</hi> and ſinful things, but alſo of things which he calls <hi>Inexpedient:</hi> And that for this very reaſon, becauſe they are not lawful, but <hi>ſinful,</hi> in worſhip; as was ſhewed in the former caſe: And any man rational would eaſily conclude, in this preſent caſe, one or both of theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That if it be unlawful, to impoſe things unlawfull or ſinful in worſhip, it is alſo unlawful to ſubmit unto them in worſhip, for the ſame reaſon.</p>
               <p>Or 2. If it be lawful to ſubmit to unlawful or ſinful things impoſed in Worſhip, it may be lawful to impoſe ſuch things in Worſhip. Yea theſe two things he hath formerly granted, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted. Firſt, That it is utterly unlawful to impoſe things Inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in Worſhip, as being ſinful there; and then, that it is as ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unlawful to ſubmit to ſinful things, if impoſed, <hi>p.</hi> 119. And yet now he undertakes a ſtranger Paradox; <q>[That it may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſubmit to things unlawful, even directly ſinful againſt a particular Scripture, not only inconvenient, and unlawful <hi>in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re:</hi>]</q> And the Argument to this purpoſe, muſt, <hi>I</hi> think, be thus framed: <q>[It may in ſome caſes be lawful, yea neceſſary to do things directly forbidden by a ſpecial poſitive Law in Scripture, therefore much rather, if forbidden, only by a general Law.]</q> The <hi>Conſequence</hi> at firſt view, ſeems reaſonable, <hi>a majore ad minus.</hi> The <hi>Antecedent</hi> he proves from Scripture Inſtances; <q>[Of the Prieſts prophaning the Sabbath, and yet innocent.]</q> and the like, of which anon. To the anſwering whereof, theſe things may be ſaid, in general.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſtill takes for granted, both that things Inexpedient, are only Inconvenient, not ſinful in Worſhip; and alſo that ſuch things (as our Ceremonies) are forbidden only by a general Law: when as we have manifeſted, in the former caſe; that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48221:24"/>by ſpecial Lawes, the ſecond and third Commandments, and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God may diſpenſe with his own Lawes, yea ſeemingly, and in part <hi>Moral</hi> Lawes; As to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to take the <hi>Goods</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and to <hi>Abraham</hi> to kill his own Son; The reaſon is, partly <hi>his Soveraignty</hi> over all Creatures, to diſpoſe of them as his own, as he pleaſes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. And partly, and chiefly, becauſe all men are <hi>Delinquents,</hi> guilty of many ſins, and <hi>Forfeitures</hi> of all their Enjoyments, and God may juſtly puniſh them, with loſs of <hi>Goods,</hi> or <hi>Life;</hi> and make what hands he pleaſes his <hi>Executioners;</hi> as in <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe: But no power on earth may command, what he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids; nor forbid, what he commands; and therefore none may <hi>forbear</hi> to do what he commands, though men forbid: nor <hi>ſubmit</hi> to do, what he forbids, though men command.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The things inſtanced in, at leaſt ſome of them, as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sacrifices, were never ſinful, in the intention of the Law of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> being Gods works, not our own; but commanded, by a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Law, and ſo their Duty to do; as being alſo a part of ſanctifying the Day, in that Ceremonial Worſhip: <q>[And in ſuch a caſe (they are the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> own words) it is not ſinful, not to fulfill a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Command, but rather a clear Obedience to God, who in the inſtance, takes off the force of the particular, in his more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Law.]</q> But can he ſhew us any general or ſpecial Law for our unneceſſary Ceremonies? If not, what Neceſſity can make them expedient, lawful, or neceſſary? But we ſay, they are <hi>ſinful,</hi> and ſo ſaies he, by conſequence, being ſo many waies <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Worſhip, and Worſhippers, as is proved on his former Tract.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thoſe Inftances, were only, in caſes of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of Gods making, either by his ſpecial <hi>Command,</hi> or by a way of <hi>Providence,</hi> caſting men into ſome neceſſity. <q>[And then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs (his own words again) the general warrant of the more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law of Neceſſity, gave a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> againſt particular Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.]</q> as will appear upon review of the Particulars: But I pray, what <hi>Neceſſity</hi> is there for the things in queſtion, either by way of Divine <hi>Command,</hi> or of his <hi>Providence?</hi> What neceſſity to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them? what to obey them, eſpecially if Inexpediently ſinful? If there be any, it is of mans making, either on the <hi>Commanders,</hi> whom the R. <hi>Caſ.</hi> hath excluded from <hi>Impoſing</hi> them: or on the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48221:25"/>
                  <hi>Submitters</hi> part, for fear of puniſhment, loſs of Livings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if ſuch Neceſſity may make Submiſſion neceſſary; the 3 Children, (as called) knew not their Liberty, they might have ſaved their Lives, by obedience to the Kings Command. I ſhall put him a Caſe or two to reſolve: There was a particular Law, that a <hi>Jew</hi> might eat no <hi>Swines-fleſh;</hi> Two Caſes of Neceſſity might happen, to enforce him to eat it; Extremity of <hi>Famine,</hi> or the <hi>Command</hi> of a <hi>Tyrant;</hi> I ſuppoſe the <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> will grant, that it was lawful, yea neceſſary in the firſt caſe to eat it, rather than ſtarve; but not in the ſecond: Or elſe thoſe Brethren ſuffered death fooliſhly, when commanded by the Tyrant to eat it. He may eaſily underſtand my meaning, and apply it. I come to his Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> is anſwered already; I only add another Caſe: Suppoſe <hi>Saul</hi> had commanded <hi>Butchers,</hi> to kill Beaſts on the Sabbath, under ſome great penalty: Here was his Neceſſity to do it, or ſuffer: Let him reſolve the Caſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was by a ſpecial Law enjoyned, that none might eat the <hi>Shew-bread,</hi> but the Prieſts: Suppoſe again, <hi>Saul</hi> had commanded <hi>David</hi> and his men, (in no neceſſity of hunger) to eat it, with a <hi>ſharp penalty</hi> upon refuſal. Here was his Neceſſity again: Might they eat it, or not? Yet in a Caſe of <hi>Providential</hi> Neceſſity of hunger, they might eat it, and are juſtified by our <hi>Saviour.</hi> The Reaſon of this Difference is, becauſe in the one caſe, <hi>Life</hi> is more neceſſary to be preſerved, than a Ceremonial Command: in the other, <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> even to a Ceremonial Commandment of God, is more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary than Life.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For <hi>Solomons</hi> Offering upon an Altar not commanded, our Divines give theſe Anſwers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he did it by Divine <hi>Direction,</hi> as he did many other things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it was in a Caſe of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> in ſuch abundance of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: and other the like Reaſons. See <hi>D. A. ubiſupra. P.</hi> 328. But there is neither <hi>Direction</hi> from God, nor any <hi>Neceſſity</hi> for our Ceremonies, more, than for many more at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> admiſſion of the Legally unclean, to the Paſſeover, fome perhaps will plead <hi>Neceſſity;</hi> but (under favour) I ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did not well: Which appears by Gods <hi>ſtriking</hi> of the people, which he would not have done, if they had not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed ſome Law; or if <hi>Neceſſity</hi> would have excuſed the matter:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48221:25"/>Yea <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had forgotten the Caſe determined by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that if a man were <hi>unclean,</hi> or in a Journey, at the juſt time of the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he might be excuſed, if he did obſerve it, the 14th. day of the next Moneth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Pauls</hi> Caſe was this, <hi>Life</hi> is more worth, more neceſſary than meat, than Corn, in ſuch a Condition.</p>
               <p>And therefore his cautelous Diſtinction, <q>[betwixt things, that are naturally, internally, materially evil, and ſuch as are unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full only by ſome poſitive Prohibitions in Scripture;]</q> is here lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle helpful to him: For we tell him, that the things in queſtion, (ſome, if not all) are <hi>naturally,</hi> internally evil; and ſome become <hi>materially</hi> evil, by ſome evil Circumſtance, (if a Prohibition will make a thing materially evil, as he ſeems to allow) and as againſt ſome ſpecial Lawes, the Second or Third Commandments, and that ſpecial Law of Nature, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. Which in his own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is a Law of Nature, which the God of Nature, will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; and ſo immutably ſuch: Things <hi>Inexpedient</hi> in Worſhip, though but Inconvenient in <hi>their uſe,</hi> are as naturally, internally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, as is any other thing prohibited by a Moral Law; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be ſubmitted to, for any external humane Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiry.</p>
               <p>That Law of <hi>Indulgence</hi> of God, <hi>[I will have Mercy</hi> (to men or Beaſts) <hi>rather than Sacrifice,]</hi> deſerves his and our <hi>wonder,</hi> and aſtoniſhment. But little to his preſent purpoſe: For it is applya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble only in Caſes of <hi>emergent</hi> and <hi>Providential</hi> Neceſſity; and then alſo, but when compared with <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> [the external and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial parts of Worſhip] as himſelf ſpeaks: <hi>e. gr.</hi> An Houſe is on fire, a Man or Beaſt is fallen into a Pit, on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> in time of publick Worſhip, in danger to periſh: Here God will have <hi>Mercy,</hi> and not <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> left off Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ching, to recover the man fallen down dead. The reaſon is evident, becauſe to preſerve <hi>Life and Goods,</hi> are <hi>Moral</hi> Commandments, and the external <hi>Exerciſes</hi> of Religion, are, in a kind, <hi>Ceremonial;</hi> And beſides, theſe may be delayed, and made good another time, but the other will periſh, if not ſpeedily ſuccoured: <q>[The poſitive (ſayes he well) muſt yield to the Natural, and Moral Duty, the leſs Neceſſity, to the more neceſſary, the leſs to the greater.]</q> But can any external <hi>neceſſity</hi> be greater, than that of <hi>Obedience</hi> unto Gods Command, by a <hi>Moral</hi> or Natural Law?</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48221:26"/>
               <p>His Application therefore, of that Rule of Indulgence, proceeds upon his too common Suppoſition <q>[Is Mercy to our Beaſt ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prized, how much more is Mercy to our ſelves, to our Nation, to the Church, to the ſoules of our people? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> This Inference were good, were the things in queſtion proved to be only <hi>Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> penally in Worſhip: but if any of them be proved <hi>unlawful,</hi> and ſinful, I ſhould argue to the contrary; <q>[Is Mercy to our Beaſts, ſo highly prized, how much more, Mercy to our own ſouls? Yea Mercy to our Nation, Church, People, in avoyding ſin againſt God?]</q> whom by ſinning, we provoke againſt all theſe. This is the way to deſtroy both <hi>Altar, Sacrifice,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> alſo: for <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> to comply together, to offend God: Mercy does well with <hi>Piety,</hi> but without it, is meer Cruelty.</p>
               <p>But much ſtreſs is laid upon the practiſe of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> in their condeſcending to <hi>Conform</hi> in ſome things, to the Ceremonial Law, and in that <hi>Decree,</hi> Acts 15. To make ſome things <hi>neceſſary,</hi> after they were aboliſhed by Chriſt his Death. This was alledged in the former Caſe, and here again. For <hi>Pauls</hi> circumciſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> and his own Obſervation of ſome <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rites, when he had preached againſt them; and that <hi>Decree,</hi> making ſome Ceremonials, not only lawful and expedient, but <hi>neceſſary,</hi> many things may be ſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though thoſe Ceremonies were <hi>dead</hi> with Chriſt, yet at that time they were not <hi>deadly</hi> till they were decently buried; and therefore were then, a while, <hi>Indifferent,</hi> to be uſed, or not, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to occaſion: <hi>Paul,</hi> that circumciſed <hi>Tim.</hi> would not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe <hi>Titus,</hi> in another caſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The reaſon of both, was one and the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>avoid offence,</hi> to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> one while to further their Converſion: to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> another while, to prevent their Apoſtacy. Now not to lay a <hi>ſtumbling</hi>-Block, or to remove it, if it be laid, is a <hi>Moral</hi> Law, to which, <hi>Poſitive,</hi> and Ceremonial Lawes muſt give place: Even <hi>Ceremonials</hi> of Divine Inſtitution, much more of mens Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For that <hi>Decree,</hi> making ſome things aboliſhed <hi>neceſſary;</hi> though enough hath been ſaid already; yet I ſhall conſider further what he ſaith: <q>[Things that are expedient, are therefore good, (it ſeemed good to us) and therefore neceſſary, theſe neceſſary things: whence thoſe very things, which we are afraid to do,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48221:26"/>becauſe Inexpedient, may poſſibly, be our Duty to do, becauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.]</q> By a contrary Inference, things that are <hi>not-expedient</hi> in Worſhip, are not good (but evil) and therefore unlawful: hence thoſe things, that we do, when expedient, we muſt be afraid to do, when, and where they are Inexpedient, that is, (in his own Gloſs) ſinful, in Worſhip: He addes, <hi>p.</hi> 147. <q>[The Apoſtles knew, that refuſing to eat things ſtrangled and bloud, at that time, eſpecially by a Law to enjoyn it, was in one Conſideration, no ſmall Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, yea a burden, as they call it, yet to prevent greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, the Apoſtacy of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Interruption of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> it ſeemed good, yea neceſſary to them, to do ſo.] Let the Reader obſerve here, his old <hi>Diverſion,</hi> (to ſay no worſe) in ſubſtituting the Word <hi>Inconvenient</hi> for <hi>Inexpedient:</hi> a penal, for a ſinful evil, and confounding the terms: For true it is, thoſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial <hi>Obſervations (dead</hi> before this time) were a <hi>burden,</hi> if Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> at that time, but not ſinful; but the cauſing or occaſioning of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of the Converted <hi>Jews,</hi> or the <hi>Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of their Converſion, by the <hi>Non-obſervation</hi> of them, for a time, were not only <hi>Inconveniencies</hi> (though ſuch alſo) but ſinful <hi>Inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies,</hi> and therefore enjoyned for a time, to prevent very great ſins: But I pray, is the <hi>Impoſition</hi> of our Ceremonies, and the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> to them, for any ſuch ends? Hear himſelf ſpeak; <q>[The ends moving thereunto, were moſt weighty, <hi>viz.</hi> The Unity of Brethren, winning Soules, the Propagation of the Goſpel, the prevention of Scandals, and the danger of the Miniſtry, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.]</q> Now as for our Ceremonies Impoſed, (or the Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things Inexpedient (ſuch as they are) which might equally be juſtified, upon the ſame grounds, which yet is by the <hi>R. Caſ</hi> peremptorily denied) not one of theſe ends can juſtly be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not the <hi>Unity</hi> of Brethren; for they are the greateſt Cauſes of our former, and preſent Diviſions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not <hi>winning</hi> of Soules: for whom ſhould they win? <hi>Papiſts?</hi> We ſee the contrary: as ſome are hardned by our coming ſo near them; ſo ſome, upon our <hi>Complyance</hi> with them, are turned <hi>Roman Catholikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Not the <hi>Propagation</hi> of the Goſpel: they hinder it (nothing more) by caſting out ſome Thouſands of able <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:48221:27"/>4. Not <hi>Prevention</hi> of Scandal; for none that judge them M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tters of <hi>Indifferency,</hi> and unneceſſary, (as moſt do, or they are very ill taught) have any juſt cauſe to be offended at our <hi>non-obſervation</hi> of them, while we are perſwaded of their unlawfulneſs: yea they occaſion much <hi>Scandal,</hi> to many truly tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Not the danger of the Miniſtry, through Perſecution; For as that was no End of the Apoſtles making that <hi>Decree,</hi> they being <hi>perſecuted,</hi> for not obſerving them, and preaching againſt them; ſo it was the end of the <hi>Falſe Teachers, Gal.</hi> 6.12. who preached up Circumciſion, to avoid Perſecution: and indeed the <hi>rigorous</hi> preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them, hath proved the greateſt <hi>danger</hi> (I muſt not ſay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution) of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ſince Q <hi>Mary's</hi> daies: Upon all theſe Reaſons, in my poor Judgment, the <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt,</hi> and his <hi>Prelates,</hi> might have done far more and better Service, to this Church and Nation, if they had endeavoured to procure an <hi>Act,</hi> for <hi>Repealing</hi> of them, than for their <hi>Impoſition,</hi> with ſo much rigour: But whiſt.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, To this Inſtance, of the Apoſtles <hi>Decree,</hi> and Practiſe, I will not plead, the great Diſtance of the two <hi>Authorities,</hi> then, and now, in impoſing things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> or Inconvenient, on the Churches: For I foreſee, what may be Anſwered: But I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell him, that very Learned men, are of Opinion, that, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,</hi> or Law, to abſtain from things offered to Idols, <hi>ſtrangled,</hi> and Bloud, is ſtill obliging to <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> (and then this Inſtance is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent.) For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. More may be ſaid to aſſert their <hi>Obligation,</hi> than for any of ours, or for all the Ceremonies of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: for this was one of the Lawes given to <hi>Noah,</hi> before the Law: revived again, by <hi>Moſes,</hi> under the Law; and now the third time <hi>ratified</hi> under the Goſpel: <hi>I</hi> know nothing ſo atteſted, except one day in ſeven, for a <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The things decreed by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſeem all either equally <hi>neceſsary,</hi> and perpetual, or all equally <hi>mutable: Theſe neceſſary things;</hi> and if <hi>mutable</hi> and arbitrary, then, <hi>Fornication</hi> may ſeem now to be, a <hi>venial ſin,</hi> as <hi>Papiſts;</hi> or an <hi>Indifferent thing,</hi> as many Proteſtants repute it, if we may judge by their Practiſe; And why things <hi>unequally</hi> lawful, or unlawful, ſhould be included in one <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, I</hi> ſhould be glad to ſee a clear Reaſon:</p>
               <p n="3">3. The reaſon of their <hi>Prohibition</hi> may ſeem (for <hi>I</hi> aſſert it not) to be <hi>Moral,</hi> and the ſame in all: As,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48221:27"/>1. Things <hi>offered to Idols,</hi> the eating of them, eſpecially in the <hi>Idol Temples,</hi> ſeems to be two waies <hi>Scandalous,</hi> firſt to the <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> to confirm them in their Idolatry, by <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Communion, and communicating with them; and next, to <hi>encourage</hi> weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to do the like, with a doubting Conſcience; thus the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle argues againſt it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10. Or elſe, let the <hi>Rev. Caſ.</hi> give a Reaſon, why it is unlawful to be <hi>preſent</hi> at, and communicate of the <hi>Romiſh Maſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The not eating of <hi>things ſtrangled, and bloud,</hi> is founded, (ſay ſome) upon a <hi>Moral</hi> Reaſon, becauſe the <hi>Life is in the Bloud,</hi> or is the Bloud, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Lev.</hi> 17.14. and that is perpetually ſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for <hi>Fornication,</hi> that, ſay moſt, is prohibited by a <hi>Moral</hi> Law, the Seventh Commandment. Now <hi>I</hi> ſhall leave this Caſe alſo, with the <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt,</hi> to be reſolved, at his leiſure. However, in the <hi>Interim,</hi> I ſhall ſay, theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That in ſome Caſes, thoſe things (beſides Fornication) are ſtill obliging, as to abſtain from eating things <hi>offered to Idols,</hi> in their <hi>Temples,</hi> if a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould live amongſt them, for the Reaſons given above: and to abſtain from things <hi>ſtrangled, and bloud,</hi> if the <hi>Jewes</hi> lived with us, if it might further their <hi>Converſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That our <hi>Caſe</hi> is not the ſame with theirs. For we abſtain not from things <hi>meerly Indifferent,</hi> or <hi>Inconvenient,</hi> but from things (in our Jugment, and his alſo) <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> that is <hi>ſinful</hi> in their uſe, in Worſhip.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not need now, to ſay any thing, to the Teſtimonies of <hi>Calvin, Pet. Martry,</hi> or <hi>Zanchy;</hi> they are all ſatisfied, by what is ſaid: and I haſten to conclude this Caſe: I hope the <hi>Rev. Caſ.</hi> will now find his <hi>Scriptures</hi> anſwered better, and himſelf better <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,</hi> by his own Principles; as my ſelf, and <hi>I</hi> believe many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are more <hi>confirmed</hi> in our Inconformity, by a <hi>prudent</hi> and <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> pondering of the Premiſes, lent us, by himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>3. <hi>Concerning the making of the firſt Declaration.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In managing the whole Diſcourſe of the <hi>Grand Caſe</hi> of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, the <hi>Rev. Author,</hi> deales not ſo fairly and fully, as was expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, nor (under Favour) ſo <hi>ingenuouſly,</hi> as is deſired: For he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries on the Buſineſs ſo <hi>precariouſly,</hi> ſo <hi>limitedly,</hi> as if he cared not, or intended not to ſatisfie all his <hi>Readers,</hi> but to <hi>wave</hi> the main
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48221:28"/>part of his work, or leave it half undone: as may thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Pag. 2, 4, 12.</note> He profeſſes, that he treats only with ſuch, as could <hi>conform,</hi> were it not for one, or both the Declarations, which <hi>I</hi> believe (for <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken with divers of them) not one of a hundred of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformers, would have done. And he ſpeakes not one word to ſatisfie thoſe, who have other Reaſons for their Inconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He profeſſes alſo, that he takes for <hi>granted,</hi> that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Liturgy and Ceremonies of the Church, are all good, and lawful, (waving the <hi>Neceſsity</hi> of them) and eſteemed ſuch by them, that refuſe conformity, <hi>p.</hi> 138. <q>[I confeſs <hi>I</hi> took the lawfulneſs of theſe, in themſelves, for granted.]</q> When as he knowes, they have all been <hi>controverted,</hi> more or leſs, well nigh theſe laſt hundred years, and are yet <hi>ſubjudice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As in his former Caſes, ſo here, all along, he takes alſo for granted, both that <hi>Inconvenient</hi> and <hi>Inexpedient</hi> are both one, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and other things controverted, are but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, and not <hi>ſinful:</hi> Now it is an eaſie thing, to make and reſolve any Caſes, if a man may have liberty to <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> what he pleaſes, to build (as a Foundation) his <hi>Reſolutions</hi> upon: And if he will give me the like liberty, to ſuppoſe all thoſe three named to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> or but to have ſomething in them, <hi>untrue,</hi> or <hi>unlawful,</hi> how eaſily can <hi>I</hi> diſſolve all his Reſolutions, and <hi>reſolve</hi> and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the contrary to his Opinion. And this <hi>Advantage</hi> we have on our ſide, that as he (<hi>I</hi> ſay not, cannot) hath not proved all things in them <hi>lawful,</hi> ſo if but one <hi>Particular</hi> in each of them, yea in the <hi>whole Book,</hi> as now eſtabliſhed, be either <hi>untrue,</hi> or <hi>unlawful,</hi> no conſcientious man can make thoſe <hi>Declarations,</hi> without palpable <hi>Diſsimulation,</hi> if not ſomething worſe. Had the <hi>Rev. Caſ.</hi> taken but half ſo much paines to prove them, and all things in them, to be <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>lawful,</hi> as he hath to perſwade us to conform, by <hi>ſuppoſing</hi> them lawful; he might have had more <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> than now he can expect: But <hi>I</hi> attend his motion.</p>
               <p>His firſt <hi>Caſe,</hi> with the <hi>Reſolution</hi> thereof, concernes not thoſe at all, that go upon other grounds, for their <hi>Inconformity.</hi> For as ſome of them, never made the former <hi>Subſcription,</hi> nor took any <hi>Oath</hi> to the <hi>Ordinary;</hi> ſo others of them, have (ſeeing juſt cauſe, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) <hi>repented</hi> of their <hi>raſh</hi> undertakings in their younger years,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48221:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>through <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and inconſideration. And as the <hi>Objections</hi> by him ſtarted, are not by theſe <hi>owned;</hi> ſo nor do they think, the <hi>Solutions</hi> by him given, will be ſatisfactory, to thoſe, for whom they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
               <p>For the firſt Objection, that though they could <hi>read</hi> the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet they do not ſo <hi>heartily</hi> like and approve them, as ſeems to be required; he reſolves it thus <q>[The Object of your aſſent, and conſent, is not the words, but things; not every word, but every thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> A poor eluſion, or rather deluſion of his Readers; For as the things are expreſſed in the words; ſo the <hi>very words,</hi> (for it was ſollicitouſly worded) are a part of the all, and every thing contained in the Book; from which if a man ſhould vary, to uſe his own apprehenſions, and expreſſions, he ſhould quickly hear of it, (as is ſaid) with both his eares. And to ſay, we cannot <hi>heartily</hi> like, and approve them, as ſeems required, and yet to give an <hi>unfeigned Aſſent,</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to all and every thing therein, ſeems to me (<hi>I</hi> ſay not <hi>Hypocriſie</hi>) a contradiction: as <hi>I</hi> ſay; <q>[I cannot heartily approve them, and yet I do heartily approve them.]</q> For what is done <hi>unfeignedly,</hi> is, I take it, done <hi>heartily, ex animo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Diſtinction, of abſolute, and comparative <hi>approbation,</hi> applyed to the Second Objection; will hardly pleaſe any Party:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not the <hi>Nonconformers;</hi> for if their ground of <hi>refuſal</hi> be good, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of but one thing therein, they can neither ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely nor comparatively aſſent and conſent thereunto: A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative <hi>Approbation</hi> of a ſinful thing, is it ſelf ſinful.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not thoſe he intends to perſwade; for an <hi>unfeigned</hi> aſſent, to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and Conſent to the <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> of all, and every thing in that <hi>Book;</hi> is as full and <hi>abſolute</hi> an Approbation (in their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion) as can be given to the <hi>Book</hi> of God, the Holy <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not to the Biſhops or <hi>Prelates;</hi> for it is ſuppoſed, that their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> in procuring and promoting the Act, was to get the <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> and that <hi>unfeigned,</hi> of all the <hi>Clergy;</hi> that is their <hi>Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation</hi> of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> of all and every thing in the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Ordination;</hi> of their <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> above <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> &amp;c. which was formerly attempted (but miſcarried) in the <hi>&amp; caetera Oath:</hi> And to ſay, <q>[you do not abſolutely approve of every thing in the Book, as that you would chuſe above all, and as beſt in it ſelf,]</q> as it will hardly pleaſe them, ſo it ſeems to put
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48221:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>a <hi>ſlurre,</hi> as upon the <hi>Book,</hi> as not the beſt (which yet was <hi>requiſite</hi> in the publick Worſhip of God) ſo upon the Compoſers of it, as if ſomething in it, were ſcarcely <hi>true,</hi> or <hi>good;</hi> but at leaſt, very <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient,</hi> and to be yielded to, only <hi>comparatively,</hi> to prevent ſome greater <hi>Inconveniencies,</hi> all which, if they pleaſed, they could have removed.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It will hardly ſatisfie the <hi>Impoſers,</hi> whoſe Deſign is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be, <hi>Unanimity,</hi> as well as <hi>Uniformity;</hi> a full and unfeigned <hi>Approbation,</hi> of all, and every thing, contained in that <hi>Bulk,</hi> or <hi>Body</hi> of Religion, as now it is come forth, and eſtabliſhed: for they three or four times (beſides this Declaration) require, in the Act, an <hi>Approbation</hi> of all and every thing; as if they intended to explain, what they mean, by <q>[thoſe milder words of Aſſent, and Conſent,]</q> as the <hi>R. Caſuiſt</hi> cals them, <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>full Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation</hi> of all.</p>
               <p>But he addes: <q>[Had the word <hi>free</hi> been in the Act, in ſtead of <hi>unfeigned</hi> (as ſome male-contents out of a vile Deſign, do buzze up and down) there had been more colour of the former Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>To let paſs the <hi>harſhneſs</hi> of his words, in this <hi>Paragraph,</hi> the rather, becauſe he hath been ſo <hi>modeſt</hi> and moderate, in his former Caſes: To the reſt <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſay: Is not <hi>unfeigned,</hi> as much, or rather more, than <hi>free?</hi> Surely what <hi>I unfeignedly</hi> aſſent to, as true, and conſent <hi>unfeignedly</hi> to, as good and lawful, I do it <hi>freely,</hi> or groſſely diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And may we not <hi>freely chuſe</hi> things that we believe are true, and good, for themſelves, and of our own accord? I believe many do ſo: <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to all and every thing as <hi>freely,</hi> as <hi>unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly,</hi> and deſire no other, no <hi>better,</hi> as thinking theſe the beſt. And I ſuppoſe, the <hi>Compoſers,</hi> if not the <hi>Impoſers,</hi> expect this free choyce, and will hardly thank them that do it, for other Reaſons; as no <hi>ſure friends</hi> to their Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But the laſt Anſwer will <q>[perfectly remove any ſuch ſcruple for ever: Let the Act interpret it ſelf: The words foregoing are theſe: Every Miniſter ſhall declare his unfeigned Aſſent, and Conſent to the uſe of all things, in the ſaid Book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not ſimply, to all things but to all things with reſpect to their uſe, to the uſe of all things in the ſaid Book.]</q> As fine and nice a <hi>Cobweb Lawn,</hi> as can be ſpun; but tranſparent, and fit only to catch <hi>weaker flies,</hi> but eaſily broken by the ſtronger. For.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48221:29"/>1. He told us before, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <q>[the Object of our Aſſent, was not words, but things, not every word, but every thing.]</q> Now <hi>Aſſent,</hi> (as was ſaid long ago) is an Act of the <hi>Underſtanding,</hi> whoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is <hi>Truth: Conſent</hi> is an Act of the <hi>Will,</hi> whoſe Object is <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse;</hi> If then, <hi>I</hi> aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained in that Book; do I not ſimply aſſent, and conſent to all things in it, as true, and good?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Can any <hi>Conſcientious</hi> man, aſſent, and conſent to the <hi>uſe</hi> of all and every thing in the <hi>Book,</hi> unleſs he be firſt convinced of the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> of all, and every thing to be uſed? And if the uſe had been intended only, in this firſt <hi>Declaration,</hi> it was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous to put it again, in the ſecond.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Intention</hi> of the <hi>Impoſers,</hi> may be collected rather from the <hi>Declaration</hi> it ſelf, than from the foregoing words, <q>[They ſhall declare their Aſſent, and Conſent, to the uſe of all, in this manner, by declaring their Aſſent and Conſent to all, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in the <hi>Book.</hi>]</q> their <hi>uniformity</hi> in practiſe, by their <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> in Judgment: For this in reaſon muſt be ſuppoſed, or they could not in any reaſon require the other, to make men practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their judgment. And if this was not their deſign, why did they ſo ſuddenly change the expreſſion, firſt to <hi>the uſe,</hi> and now to all and every thing?</p>
               <p n="4">4. And why do they afterwards, ſo often uſe thoſe words, He ſhall declare his <hi>Approbation,</hi> his <hi>Approbation</hi> of all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which muſt be meant of the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of all, as well as of the uſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this nice diſtinction of <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> cannot be applied to all, and every thing, in this firſt Declaration: For, every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, though he aſſent and conſent to the <hi>uſe</hi> of all in the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> yet he cannot properly aſſent and conſent to the uſe of all and every thing contained in the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Ordination:</hi> for no Miniſter under a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> can Ordain a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> or Deacon: It muſt then neceſſarily be taken, for their Aſſent and Conſent to the Truth and Goodneſs of the <hi>Way of Ordination</hi> by Biſhops, and of the three <hi>Orders</hi> of Church Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus much of the firſt Declaration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>4. <hi>Concerning the making of the Second Declaration.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> or ſecond Declaration, there are three main things that fall into conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:48221:30"/>["1. The taking up Armes againſt the King.</p>
               <p n="2">"2. Corformity to the Liturgy.</p>
               <p n="3">"3. The Solemn League and Covenant.]</p>
               <p>Of which, we know not what is beſt, and ſafeſt, whether to <hi>speak,</hi> or be <hi>ſilent:</hi> If we <hi>ſpeak</hi> not very warily, we run upon a rock of Law; if <hi>ſilent,</hi> we may be ſuſpected, to betray our own <hi>Innocence:</hi> To the two firſt, we ſhall ſay very little, to the laſt a little more.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the firſt, we humbly cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve leave to ſay this little: They that refuſe to make this <hi>Declaration,</hi> do not ſtick at this, but are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to profeſs <q>[That as they never did take up Arms againſt the King (which was conſtantly denied by the Parliament, in all their Declarations, and Proteſtations, and they think, in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant it ſelf) but for the King. So they hold it utterly unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for Subjects, ſo to do.]</q> and hold it (as now by Law it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined) a <hi>Trayterous Poſition,</hi> ſo to aſſert; which they were taught before to <hi>abhor,</hi> both by <hi>Scripture,</hi> by the <hi>Oathes</hi> of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Supremacy, and by the <hi>Solemn Covenant</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond of <hi>Conforming</hi> to the Practiſe of the Liturgy, as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is ſaid here by the <hi>Caſuiſt;</hi> ſo it is ſufficiently diſcuſſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, according to the judgment of Non-conformiſts, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Caſe: The Reſult whereof is this: <q>[If there be any thing, any one thing in it, either untrue, or unlawful, they dare not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their unfeigned Aſſent, and Conſent to it, or the practiſe of it.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That of the Covenant is the <hi>Mountain</hi> to be removed, not by the <hi>Faith,</hi> but by the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>skill</hi> of the Learned <hi>Caſuiſt:</hi> And this is acknowledged by the <hi>Refuſers</hi> of this Declaration, to be the main <hi>Buſineſs</hi> of conteſt: and that, not in the <hi>whole,</hi> but in one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle thereof, in the ſecond <hi>Article:</hi> as will appear.</p>
               <p>In three things, the <hi>Rev. Caſuiſt,</hi> and they, are fully agreed.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[1. That a Covenant both illegally Impoſed, and illegally ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, may bind the Takers.] That muſt be (I ſuppoſe) from the, either neceſſity,</q> or lawfulneſs of the matter covenanted.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[2. That the Covenant in queſtion, doth not bind to an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to alter, or meddle with the State-Government.]</q> No, for it is as ſtrong an eſtabliſhment of it, as can be made, in the third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[3. That if the Alteration or Extirpation of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be the main Buſineſs of the Covenant, and this be lawful
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48221:30"/>it doth ſo far bind the takers: if not lawful, they are ſo far diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from the Obligation of it.]</q> Now evident it is, that the <hi>Anti-Covenanters,</hi> as they do not except againſt any <hi>Article</hi> of it, but the <hi>Second;</hi> ſo not againſt any part or particle of this ſecond <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> but only this, <q>[That Covenants to endeavour the extirpation of Prelacy, that is the Hierarchy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> This, this is the <hi>Helena,</hi> for which they contend ſo vigorouſly: This the <hi>eye-ſore,</hi> that ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperates their Spirits. They do not, I think, they dare not deny the Obligation, of the other <hi>Articles,</hi> nor of the other parts of the ſecond, <q>[as to the extirpation of Popery, Superſtition, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Schiſm, Prophaneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Much leſs will they deny the Obligation of the third <hi>Article,</hi> 
                  <q>[to defend and preſerve the Kings Majeſties Perſon, and Authority, the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> They may ſay, they were bound to thoſe, either by the <hi>Oaths</hi> of Allegiance and Supremacy, or by the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> as Native Subjects: I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How many took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> that never took thoſe <hi>Oaths?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Oath was made, at leaſt in this Article, to <hi>God</hi> only, <hi>P.</hi> 114.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The other is true, but then it muſt be granted, that the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> though illegally impoſed, and taken, (the matter being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or lawful) addes a new <hi>Obligation,</hi> being made <hi>to God</hi> only: And as the latter does not voyd the former, ſo the former does not diſoblige from the latter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I add, we were bound (before the Covenant was impoſed or taken) by the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and our <hi>Covenant</hi> of Baptiſm, and <hi>Scripture</hi>-Rules, <q>[to endeavour the Reformation of Religion, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, in our places, and Callings, and conſequently to extirpate Popery, Superſtition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> though we had never taken the Covenant: Hence I would infer, (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, for <hi>Diſputations</hi> ſake, not <hi>poſitively</hi> aſſerting it,) <q>[If the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Government, as then it ſtood, be equally unlawful, with Popery, Superſtition, and the reſt: we are by a former Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God, bound equally to endeavour the alteration, and extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of it;]</q> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> is but a new <hi>Cord,</hi> added to ſtrengthen that Obligation. <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know it is not ſafe for any wiſe man, to ſay much, in <hi>Defence</hi> of the Covenant, there being an <hi>Act</hi> publiſhed to diſſolve, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null it, as unlawful, in ſeveral reſpects: I ſhall therefore aſſert no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>poſitively</hi> for it, or againſt the preſent <hi>Church-Government;</hi> but humbly crave leave, to proceed <hi>ſuppoſitively,</hi> as the <hi>Rev. Caſ.</hi> does:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48221:31"/>For all his large <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> to perſwade to that part of the ſecond <hi>Declaration,</hi> is founded upon this Suppoſition; not that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> and ſo <hi>neceſsary,</hi> (for upon ſuppoſal of that, a <hi>Covenant,</hi> or <hi>endeavour</hi> to alter or extirpate it, were utterly unlawful:) but only <hi>Lawful</hi> or <hi>Indifferent:</hi> And then, I ſhould, for my part, grant, that it was <hi>unlawful</hi> to <hi>Covenant,</hi> much more to <hi>endeavour</hi> to alter and <hi>extirpate</hi> it, without the Supream Authority of the Nation: And let me but have the like liberty, to <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> (let others that can, make it good) that the <hi>Government,</hi> is, by the Word of God, <hi>unlawful;</hi> and upon that <hi>Suppoſition</hi> and Perſwaſion, as I may not own it, by <hi>Aſsent, Conſent,</hi> or <hi>Subſcription,</hi> ſo all his Arguments, to prove the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of making this Declaration, are to me, of no force; till he prove it, either <hi>neceſsary,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> (which he goes not about to do, but all along takes for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which, I think, he ought not to do) for <hi>their ſakes,</hi> who ſcruple the Lawfulneſs of it.</p>
               <p>That he does <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> the Lawfulneſs, (for he <hi>waves</hi> to plead the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this Government, as others begin to do, both in the former, and in theſe Caſes) appeares in ſeveral paſſages: ["as <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>ſ.</hi> 10. and <hi>p.</hi> 52. Admit that Epiſcopal Government was <hi>Res</hi>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Indifferens, &amp; Mutabilis,</hi> when ſworn againſt, <hi>p.</hi> 80. If the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſworn againſt, be not unlawful. And <hi>p.</hi> 138. I confeſs <hi>I</hi> took the Lawfulneſs of the Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in themſelves, for granted.]</q> Importing (as <hi>I</hi> think) if the things were unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, then the fault of the <hi>Covenant</hi> was not in the <hi>Matter</hi> (it might be lawful to covenant, and endeavour the extirpation of them) but in the <hi>Manner,</hi> that it was <hi>illegally</hi> impoſed, and taken, without the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſee him ſtate the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>It ſeemes, ſome <hi>Covenanters</hi> granting, that if the <hi>Matter</hi> of the Covenant, was but in this Particular unlawful, the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf, was ſo far unlawful, and loſt its Obligation; do call aloud for ſtrong Reaſons, to prove the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of the Matter, in this particular: The Learned <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> now undertakes to give ſuch as he hath; but (under favour) quite beſides the Queſtion by them intended: For they ſuppoſe, not only the <hi>Government</hi> to be unlawful, but alſo the <hi>Extirpation</hi> of it (which is the <hi>Matter</hi> now in queſtion) to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: and require Reaſons to prove it materially unlawful. But his Caſe, and Reaſons reſpect the <hi>Takers,</hi> whether they may Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and endeavour to extirpate the Government, without the King:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48221:31"/>for ſo he ſaies: <q>[My work is, in ſhort, to prove, that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſo far as it engageth the Takers of it, againſt Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and for the change of it, is unlawful, and ſinful, in the Matter of it.]</q> The <hi>Matter</hi> is one thing; whether it be lawful (for any) to extirpate the <hi>Government</hi> (ſuppoſed unlawful:) The <hi>Takers</hi> are another; whether it be lawful for <hi>private</hi> men, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this, without the King: The former may be lawful, when the latter is not ſo: And here he ſlides ſecretly from the <hi>Matter</hi> to the Manner; from the <hi>Thing</hi> to the <hi>Perſons;</hi> as will appear.</p>
               <p>For mark his Diſtinction, whereon, he ſayes, he <hi>fixes</hi> the foot of all the Arguments following: <q>[The things ſworn to be done, may be either ſuch, as is ſimply unlawful for any to do, or <hi>quoad nos,</hi> when though not ſinful in the firſt Conſideration; yet to ſuch perſons it is ſinful.]</q> Mark this, it is in true ſenſe, as if he had ſaid, the <hi>Matter</hi> may be lawful and laudable in it ſelf, and lawful to be done, but not <hi>lawfully</hi> (for <hi>Manner)</hi> by ſome Perſons: For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; The <hi>Government,</hi> being not <hi>neceſsary,</hi> but <hi>Indifferent</hi> and mutable, may lawfully be altered, yea <hi>extirpated,</hi> by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> but not by ſingle or private perſons: (<hi>I</hi> doubt his <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours</hi> will give him little thankes for this <hi>Intimation.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now ſee, how he applies this Diſtinction; <q>[If the Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government, be unlawful, either in the firſt or abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſenſe, or elſe as to thoſe, that did thus covenant; if either way, it be found unlawful, ſo far the Covenant is ſinful in the very Matter of it.]</q> This is ſtrange from ſo Learned a <hi>Caſuiſt:</hi> For if it be <hi>abſolutely</hi> unlawful to extirpate the Government, then it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to Covenant ſo to do; but if it be unlawful only as to ſuch <hi>perſons,</hi> will your Learning ſuffer you to aſſert, it is ſinful in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Matter</hi> of it? And is there not another way, granted by your ſelf, to free the <hi>Matter</hi> from fault? You may pleaſe to review, how you ſecre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly beg the Queſtion, that it is ſimply unlawful to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the <hi>Government,</hi> which you cannot ſay unleſs you make it <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, Jure Divino,</hi> (which you have twice <hi>waved</hi> to do.) And if it be only <hi>lawful,</hi> and not neceſſary, (as you ſeem to be of opinion) you will not deny (unleſs you deny a <hi>Priviledge</hi> of Parliament) but it is <hi>mutable,</hi> and may be altered by a Lawful Authority: much more if it be it ſelf unlawful: And if ſo; then the <hi>Matter</hi> of the Covenant, is not ſinful; but the Crime will fall only on the <hi>Takers,</hi> which reſpects the manner. But on the other ſide; If it be in it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48221:32"/>ſelf <hi>unlawful,</hi> the extirpation of it, is alſo <hi>lawful,</hi> and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting to endeavour it, even by private perſons, may be <hi>materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> lawful, by former Obligations to God. Or let him give us a ſolid Reaſon, why the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſhall bind us, to extirpate <hi>Popery, Superſtition,</hi> &amp;c. And in the ſame <hi>Article,</hi> ſhall not oblige us, to extirpate an <hi>unlawful Government, I</hi> mean, ſuppoſing it to be ſuch.</p>
               <p>There are therefore no ſmall miſadventures in his Ninth <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, p.</hi> 25. As,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <q>[1. That the immediate Queſtion, and that which moſt near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concernes the Covenanters, is not, whether the thing ſworn be in it ſelf lawful, but whether it be ſo to them?]</q> But by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, the firſt Queſtion concernes them moſt: for if the thing ſworn be <hi>unlawful</hi> in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> it renders it <hi>ipſo Facto</hi> unlawful for them to ſwear: But if the thing be lawful in it ſelf, yea <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> for ſome to do, yet it may not be lawful for them to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it; as he told us, a little before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the thing be <hi>materially</hi> lawful, and more, if it be <hi>neceſsary</hi> for all to do, in their <hi>places</hi> and callings, there lies no guilt upon 'them, ['firſt to purpoſe, and then to ſwear to do their Duty;] that is, to do that which God hath ſome way or other commanded them to do.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not reaſonable to ſay. <q>[As it is unlawful for us, it goes into the matter of the Covenant which we take.]</q> For the <hi>Matter</hi> may be lawful, as to execute <hi>Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. and yet unlawful for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons. And then the <hi>Conſequence,</hi> which he would infer hence, is inconſequent. <q>[That that which is unlawful to us, if ſworn, doth make that Oath, as ours, unlawful in it ſelf, that is, in the Matter of it.]</q> It makes the <hi>Oath</hi> unlawful indeed, but not in the <hi>Matter,</hi> which may in it ſelf be lawful, but in the <hi>Manner,</hi> as <hi>ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The prime and main Queſtion then, ſhould have been, <q>[Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Government covenanted againſt, be neceſſary, lawful, or unlawful?]</q> All which, he <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> waves to reſolve: for ſo he ſaies, <q>[I ſhall not need to diſpute, whether the Government of our Church be ſo neceſſary by a <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> as that it is unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by men: or that it is ſinful in it ſelf, to endeavour the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of it, <hi>p.</hi> 25.]</q> Truly, I believe, he anſwers not the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation</hi> or deſires of ſome of his own Party, that he does not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this <hi>Taske.</hi> And I can aſſure him, that if he had proved
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48221:32"/>that by two or three ſtrong Arguments, his Non-conforming Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, would have much thanked him, and ingenuouſly have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, the Covenant in the <hi>Matter</hi> of it was unlawful: But why would he not for <hi>their ſakes,</hi> give ſome ſolid <hi>Reaſous,</hi> to prove the <hi>Government</hi> lawful? And then perhaps, they would have yielded, the Covenant to be unlawful in the <hi>manner,</hi> if not alſo, ſo far in the Matter. It were no hard work, to conjecture, why he choſe rather to prove the <hi>Covenant</hi> to be unlawful, with reſpect to the <hi>Perſons,</hi> that impoſed, and took it; and took it for granted, the <hi>Government</hi> was, and is in it ſelf lawful. But <hi>I</hi> ſhall forbear to expreſs my thoughts. <hi>I</hi> ſhall tell him what <hi>I</hi> obſerved on his former <hi>Caſes,</hi> that he did not in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> take upon him to vindicate our <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> but kept aloof <hi>in Theſi,</hi> in <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and <hi>Inexpedient</hi> things (which yet he could not do, but he muſt <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> for Diſputes ſake, the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> were ſuch things, though he inſtanced not in any of them) becauſe it was both <hi>hard</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> them lawful; and unſafe or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, to <hi>inſinuate</hi> they were unlawful: I ſay no more.</p>
               <p>But now, ſeeing he knowes, that the Governments <hi>Lawfulneſs,</hi> hath been long controverted at home and abroad, by very Learned and Pious men, and Churches: I ſhould think, it had been <hi>reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and expedient, in this ſo great an undertaking, as to perſwade <hi>Diſsenters</hi> to Conformity, not to <hi>preſume,</hi> and take for granted, the things are lawful, but by ſome <hi>irrefragable</hi> Arguments, though few, to prove that they are ſo: Or elſe to give them liberty to produce theirs, to prove them unlawful; which is not ſafe for either Party: Yet to ſuppoſe a while, and for Diſputations ſake, to take them (the Government in ſpecial) to be unlawful; and then, thereby to manifeſt how weak, and <hi>unſatisfying,</hi> all his Reaſonings are, to ſuch as take them ſo to be: This one Anſwer may be an impenetrable ſhield, <q>[The Government is to us unlawful; and therefore we cannot, we dare not aſſent, conſent, or ſubſcribe unto it.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>To follow the Rev. Author, in all his Particulars, would be both <hi>dangerous,</hi> and <hi>tedious,</hi> when one Anſwer muſt ſo often be repeated, which may ſerve once for all, <hi>It is to us unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For hence, 1. It matters not at all <q>[Whether the Covenant in this part (or others) was impoſed, and taken, by a Body in Parliament, or by Single perſons, or by the King himſelf without them.]</q> For the thing it ſelf being <hi>unlawful,</hi> they were bound, without any Covenant taken (but more with it) to alter, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to extirpate it, every one in his <hi>Place,</hi> and <hi>Calling.</hi> A ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48221:33"/>Duty, concerning all perſons, more, or leſs; as it may and muſt be done, by every one <hi>ſingle</hi> (I ſay ſtill, in his Place and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) ſo it may be covenanted to be endeavoured, by one or more together. This is Aſſerted by a Learned <hi>Epiſcopal Doctor</hi> 
                  <q>[That to fulfil the expreſs Commandment of God, no man doubteth, but that a <hi>Covenant</hi> may be made, not only without, but againſt the Command of a Prince.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If the thing be in it ſelf <hi>unlawful,</hi> then to Covenant to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour (each in his Place and Calling) to extirpate a ſinful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is not againſt, <q>[1. The Kings Rights, either as S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Governour, or as Legiſlator. 2. Nor againſt the Lawes of the Land. 3. Nor againſt the Priviledges of Parliament. 4. Nor againſt the liberties of the ſubjects. 5. Nor againſt any former obligations.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>God hath the firſt <hi>Obligation</hi> upon us, by our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion (<hi>I</hi> ſay ſtill, each in his Place and Calling.) <q>[To <hi>contend earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude <hi>v.</hi> 3.]</q> And conſequently to endeavour to remove and root out, all <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> Worſhip, Diſcipline, or <hi>Government</hi> contrary thereunto: <hi>I</hi> ſhall not ſo much diſtruſt the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> of any Reader; much leſs the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the Learned <hi>Caſuiſt,</hi> as that they will deny the former <hi>Conſequences</hi> (upon my borrowed, or begged Suppoſition) or that they are not eaſily <hi>able,</hi> if but willing, to make <hi>Application</hi> thereof, to all the Particulars named.</p>
               <p>Much more might have been ſaid, to many things, but I am warned by anothers Harm, <q>[Not to fly too near the Candle, leſt I be ſcorched by the Flame.]</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>5. The Concluſion. <hi>Concerning the Lawfulneſs of Re-Ordination,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>There is one thing (and but one thing, he ſaies) more, in the <hi>Condition of Law,</hi> required of Miniſters, by the Act, and that is, <q>[Re-Ordination of ſuch, as were Ordained by Presbyters only, and Ordination of others, by Biſhops.]</q> And both theſe are much ſcrupled by ſome, men of hopeful, and very uſeful parts: The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort, becauſe they believing Biſhops, as ſuch, and as a diſtinct Order from Presbyters, to be unlawful, dare not come under un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authorized hands: The former, becauſe they judge their Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on valid, by Presbyters; and dare no more be re-ordained, then re-baptized. And indeed, if their Ordination by Presbyters, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid, all their Miniſterial Acts, by vertue of that Ordination, are null, (as ſome <hi>Prelates</hi> have told them:) and if not they themſelves,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48221:33"/>yet thoſe baptized by them, muſt be re-baptized, or elſe they are ſcarce Chriſtians: which ſeems very harſh Doctrine, from them, who as thy cry out of Anabaptiſts, for Re-baptization; ſo in ſome Caſes, allow a Woman to baptize: Let them conſider it: and <hi>I</hi> attend him. He uſes many Reaſons, to perſwade the firſt ſort (though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the ſecond) not to ſtick at Re-ordination. As,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <q>[1. Conſidering, that Liberty is not denied them, to keep their own ſenſe, whether Ordination by Presbyters, is valid, or not.]</q> This is, as if the Children of Anabaptiſts, being forced by Law, to be baptized, ſhould perſwade their Parents to ſuffer it, conſidering that Liberty is not denied them, to keep their own ſenſe, whether this Baptiſm is valid, or not: and they may rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them, when at Age. Does an Ordinance of God, depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens ſenſe thereof? Or may men dally with it in this manner? and not take his Name in vain? However, ſome Biſhops tell them, their firſt Ordination, with all the Acts thereof are null, and bid them repent of all. Now if their Ordination be judged by them, to be valid, they in repeating of it, offend againſt the Word, the Ordainers, and thoſe Churches that have no Biſhops, as making theirs, no Miniſters, no Churches. If they judge it not valid, they offend (if but ignorantly) againſt the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt; who hath placed Ordination in a Presbytery. Biſhops themſelves being firſt Ordained by ſuch, (even B. <hi>Timothy,</hi> if a B. he was) as <hi>Hierome</hi> (with the Scripture) hath proved, and others follow him therein.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <q>[2. The Act (he ſaies) makes it ſelf no judge of the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Presbyters, in forreign Churches.]</q> In words, and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it does not; but implicitly, and conſequentially it does; Elſe, why doth it ſo ſtrictly, ſo rigorouſly, require Ordination by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop? But as making the former null, and invalid, to any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Acts? Yea ſome Prelatical men, ſtick not to affirm thoſe Churches to be none, that want Biſhops.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <q>[3. There is no other way (ſaies he) to exerciſe their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, in this Church, by Law, or to entitle them to a Charge, or the Profits thereof.]</q> How true this is, appeares, in that many Prieſts, ordained by Popiſh Biſhops, are admitted to all thoſe, without Re-ordination, It is a ſad thing, that a Presbytery of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Learned, Orthodox men, ſhould not find the ſame favour with Proteſtants. But if Ordination by Presbyters, be Evangelical, it ſhould ſeem reaſonable, it ſhould be made Legal: No Law of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48221:34"/>man ought to countermand the Inſtitutions of Jeſus Chriſt. And what is this, but a kind of Independant Principle, on the one ſide, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and require Re-ordination of their Miniſters (ſuch as it is) as oft as they remove from one congregation to another: And on the other ſide, a kind of Anabaptiſtical Fancy, &amp; practiſe, who allow, &amp; require rebaptization of thoſe baptized by our epiſcopa Miniſters. And laſtly it ſeems a too near Complyance with <hi>Rome;</hi> where they re-ordain thoſe of ours, that convert, or apoſtate to them, though ordained by our Biſhops, as our Biſhops re-ordain thoſe ordained by Presbyters. This Retaliation may ſeem juſt, and reaſonable, at leaſt from God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To ſave himſelf a further Labour, he refers us to Mr. <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phries</hi> Juſtification of his own, and others Re-ordination: Alas poor Soul? A worſe Perſwaſive could ſcarce have been brought: whoſe Tracts are judged by ſome very weak, and by others ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently confuted; and which is more, ſtrongly, really contradicted, by a moſt vehement Abjuration, of his 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Ordination by a Biſhop.</p>
               <p>Concerning his own ſolemn Profeſſion and Subſcription, <hi>ex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo,</hi> 
                  <q>[That he hath not uſed one Argument, but what he judges convincing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> I, for my part, am in Charity bound, and willing to believe him: For upon his <hi>Suppoſition,</hi> I ſhould eaſily be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my ſelf; that is, <q>[if the Government, Liturgy, Ceremonies of this Church, be in all, and every thing, true and lawful,]</q> (which are indeed all concerned, and ſuppoſed in the Declarations, but not by him at all proved, but confeſſedly here, taken for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) I ſhould be ready to profeſs Conformity to them; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding many <hi>Inconveniences</hi> in them: But when his Oppoſites take many things to be unlawful, and he preſumes to take them all for lawful; he may perhaps perſwade ſome, that are of his mind, (which few are) but cannot in reaſon hope to make them his Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, who judge any thing in them, unlawful.</p>
               <p>There are ſome other things here repeated, which have been ſpoken to elſewhere, and I paſs them by. I have one humble requeſt to make to the Rev. Caſuiſt; and I have done: That at his next leiſure, he will be pleaſed to give ſome few new Arguments, (for the old, we think, are inſufficient, and ſufficiently anſwered) to prove, I ſay not all and every thing in the Declarations to be neceſſary (that would be too hard a Task) but to prove, the things controverted, the Government, Liturgie, Ceremonies to be Lawful, according to the Word of God; and I ſhall engage my ſelf, and what little Credit I have, either to give him a fair, and full Anſwer, with Meekneſs, and Modeſty; or, if I cannot, to yield my ſelf his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48221:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
